<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Christians daily monitor to the performance of personal and relative duties With a resolution of some cases of conscience. Published for the benefit of young persons; By Joseph Church. Together with so much of Mr. Samuel Hierons catechisme, as concerns second table duties.</title>
            <author>Church, Josiah.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 159 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 83 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79559</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3986B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230947</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896602</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896602</idno>
            <idno type="VID">134628</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79559)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 134628)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2424:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Christians daily monitor to the performance of personal and relative duties With a resolution of some cases of conscience. Published for the benefit of young persons; By Joseph Church. Together with so much of Mr. Samuel Hierons catechisme, as concerns second table duties.</title>
                  <author>Church, Josiah.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 141, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Tho. Parkhurst, at the sign of the Bible upon London Bridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Joseph Church = Josiah Church.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Sion College Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Duty --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:134628:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:134628:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Chriſtians DAILY MONITOR To the performance of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal and Relative Duties.</p>
            <p>With a Reſolution of ſome Caſes of CONSCIENCE.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for the benefit of Young Perſons;</p>
            <p>By <hi>Joſeph Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with ſo much of Mr. <hi>Samuel Hierons</hi> Catechiſme, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns ſecond Table Duties.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Bible</hi> upon <hi>London</hi> Bridge, 1669.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:134628:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:134628:2"/>
            <head>TO M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> 
               <hi>Elizabeth Papilion,</hi> Eldeſt Daughter to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Thomas Papilion,</hi> The Authour wiſhes increaſe of Grace and Peace.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He intent of this Dedication, is not to tell the World how hopefull and towardly a Child you are, but <hi>partly for mine own ſake,</hi> to teſtifie my ſenſe of thoſe many kindneſſes I have received from your Parents; which I cannot ſee any poſſibility I ſhould ever require, and the leaſt I can do is to acknowledg. Low<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Parents do accept from a poor hand a ſmall kindneſs that is ſhewed to
<pb facs="tcp:134628:3"/> their Children: Even God himſelf our Heavenly Father, becauſe our good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs extends not to him, accepts of what we do to his Children; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe my thankfulneſs cannot aſcend, I was willing that it ſhould deſcend, ever judging it a true principle, <hi>If I cannot do the good I would, to do what good I can.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But for your ſakes alſo do I Dedicate this ſmall Book to you:</p>
            <p n="1">1. To lay an obligation upon you to anſwer the means you enjoy in a good education, that the prayers, pains and coſt your Parents are at with you may not be loſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That you might have a Daily Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitor of your Duty to God and Man. You are not ſure to have Father or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alwayes with you, or Miniſters, but theſe things if they ſink into your heart, will abide with you to comfort and counſel you. I do therefore exhort you to a frequent and ſerious r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ding of them, with prayer unto God, that
<pb facs="tcp:134628:3"/> they may be bleſſed to you; and if no other ſhould gain by them, yet if you do, I ſhall not altogether repent my pains: But if others ſhould gain by them, and you not, you and I both ſhall have cauſe of grief and ſhame. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don my plainneſs with you; I ſpeak not this as diſtruſting the Grace of God in you, (which I pray may grow up with you more and more, and abound in you:) but as one I love in the Lord, to warn you, and admoniſh you, that you may not begin in the ſpirit, and end in the fleſh. Some of theſe things you have heard diſcourſed to you, and ſome of them in publick, and there are ſome that I have collected from others, which owe nothing to me but the meer order and form of them, of which I have given an account by prefixing the two firſt letters of their names. I know you have many other uſefull, and ſpiritual Books by you; let not this take you off from them, nor them, or this, make you neglect the reading of
<pb facs="tcp:134628:4"/> the Scriptures, and the orderly reading of them, according to an example you have daily before your eyes: For all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Books are written to give light to the Scripture, and to ſtir us up to the practiſe of thoſe duties there laid down. I ſhall trouble you no further now, but commend you and this Treatiſe to the bleſſing of the Almighty; And Reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Souls, and your Faiths Servant in the Lords Work,</hi> Joſ. Church.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:134628:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT was not becauſe the World needed Books that I appear in Print, or if it did, there are (bleſſed be God) e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough others, more able, and fit to ſupply its wants: But one great induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt to me to Print, was the need I ſtood in of the Preſs to eaſe me of the labour of tranſcribing theſe things for my own near Relations and Friends; and were there not a kind of neceſſity of multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the number of Copies beyond what would have ſerved my particular occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, (to any one will make uſe of that ingenious Invention of <hi>Printing,</hi>) I could very well have been contented to have been conſined within the limits
<pb facs="tcp:134628:5"/> forementioned. I would intreat thee therefore to conſider, that theſe things were first written and laid together for the private uſe and benefit of ſome young perſons: And my touching upon ſo many ſubjects, and with brevity, was with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to that age; for variety and brevity do moſt pleaſe them: and if any think by brevity I am guilty of obſcurity, let it put them upon meditation, and beating things out in their own thoughts, or elſe enquiry of others what ſuch a thing means, before they condemn me: But I am not conſcious to my ſelf of that crime, for though I have endeavoured to ſpeak pertinently and ſhortly, yet I have alſo done it plainly. I have ventured at ſome caſes of conſcience, which I obſerved did frequently occur among ſober good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; not that I think my ſelf able for that kind of divinity, but if by any means I might provoke ſome of my able Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to travel in that ſo much wanted and deſired work of Caſuiſtical Divinity: And if I have not wrote what may give
<pb facs="tcp:134628:5"/> full ſatisfaction, yet I hope I have taken the ſafe way, and ſaid that may ſtay the violence of the diſtreſs if rightly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, till they meet with that interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a thouſand, that ſhall ſpeak a word in ſeaſon to him that is weary. I am very ſenſible, that whoſoever doth appear in <hi>Print,</hi> layes himſelf open to the laſh of every mans tongue: Some will criticize, ſome will cenſure, others will deride and ſcorn, but all theſe ſhall hurt themſelves more then me. I do not expect better mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure then thoſe that were far my betters had before me, and have at this day. It is vaſtly more comfortable to have a mans words and name reproached innocently, then to cenſure and wrest proudly and uncharitably, what is well meant, and upon examination will be found well-ſpoken, if it be but well taken.</p>
            <p>To pleaſe all is impoſſible, to pleaſe men in their ſins is wicked, and to pleaſe good men in theſe dayes, wherein there is ſuch a conſumption of charity, is very difficult. As for thoſe that are learned
<pb facs="tcp:134628:6"/> (if any ſuch ſhould ſtoop ſo low as to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe theſe things) it may be if they find no beams of light, they may find ſome ſparks of fire to kindle their affections, and to beget ſome ardour and fervency of deſire to add to their knowledge practiſe: as for any other fire of contention and ſtrife, I truſt they ſhall find none: I ſhould think the worſe of my ſelf as long as I live, if I ſhould be really guilty of that. O that we could all avoid <hi>ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um partium,</hi> the eſpouſing particular opinions and intereſts, and labour after an univerſal charity to all that love our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and ſilence our own private ſentiments which might cauſe a publick diſturbance, which we muſt not expect till we ſee more piety. For the Schooles have long ago told us, <hi>Rivulus charitatis oritur ex fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e pietatis,</hi> That the ſtream of charity to our Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, comes from the fountain of piety towards God: If therefore thou art an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>my to true piety, thou art at the ſame time an enemy to charity. For the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting
<pb facs="tcp:134628:6"/> therefore true piety in young perſons and comers in, I have offered my endeavours in the enſuing Diſcourſe: That if this preſent Generation, after all their cultivating ſhould bring forth no fruit, nor admit of any melioration, yet the ſeedlings and young plants might draw in a more benigne juyce, and ſhoot up and bring forth more and better fruits. It is a general complaint, that Relations prove ſo bad; and indeed to find a man faithful in all Relations, is to find a rare Jewel. Nothing more honours God and the Goſpel, then when thoſe that profeſs it, live up to the duty commanded them in their Relations, as nothing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhonours God more, ſhames the Goſpel, ruines families, then undutifulneſs and unfaithfulneſs in Relations. No plainer proof of our ſincerity in our Religion then this is. Thou canſt not be a good Chriſtian if thou art not a good Child, a good Servant, a good Maſter or Miſtris, a good Subject, a good Husband or Wife. The ſame God that commands to be a good
<pb facs="tcp:134628:7"/> Chriſtian, commands thee to fill up the duties of the other alſo, as he calls thee to them; and one great cauſe of the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of theſe duties, and the decay of them, is the neglect of Catechizing in private families, which till it be conſcientiouſly practiſed, all publick preaching and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techizing will be the leſs ſucceſsful.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon whoſe account ſoever the neglect of this doth lie, I am ſure it will not be found light one day; and one mans omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his duty, will be no excuſe then for thy neglecting thine. I have here offered a plain ſhort Catechiſme of the heads of ſecond Table Duties: <hi>I</hi> made choice of this Authour, as one who lies liable, as I know of, to no exception; the Catechiſm having been reprinted ſeveral times with good approbation, and alſo becauſe his anſwers are for the most part the words of Scripture pertinently quoted and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon which account as the duties herein preſſed come with more authority, ſo the learner is accuſtomed to Scripture phraſes and language, for want of which,
<pb facs="tcp:134628:7"/> and the unbounded libertie many give to their fancy, we have ſo many uncouth, wild, extravagant and offenſive expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions even in Religious performances: Which however weak ones may account the height of devotion, yet riper judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſober Chriſtians know them to be nothing elſe but the ſtatulency of fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. I exhort thee therefore <hi>(Chriſtian Reader)</hi> to hold fast the form of ſound words, get thy heart ſtocked with ſound knowledge, and take heed of phraſeologie in Religion, which is a minting and coyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing new expreſſions, and differencing our ſelves from others by an affected ſtile or form of ſpeaking, and making people believe we have attained more light then others, when as indeed when theſe notions come to be examined and weighed in the ballance of Truth, they are worth no more then the traſh and trumpery that the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals Sumpter horſes carried (a ſtory ſo well known, it needs but naming.) And this is all will be found among the <hi>Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſts</hi> of this Age, the <hi>Behmeniſts, Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celſians,
<pb facs="tcp:134628:8"/> Familiſts,</hi> &amp;c. Thus I have in brief, with plainneſs of heart, given thee an account of this Work, which I ſhall pray to God may be acceptable to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſucceſsfull to their ſpiritual edification, in Knowledge, Faith, Love and obedience. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in the Lord,</hi> Joſ. Church.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:134628:8"/>
            <head>The Chriſtians daily Monitor. To the performance of perſonal and rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Duties, &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>§. <hi>1.</hi> Of Humility.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Umility is a foundation grace: to <hi>encreaſe this grace,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare thy ſelf,</p>
               <p>With the <hi>brute creatures,</hi> that have onely ſenſe, yet they keep the Law of their Creation.</p>
               <p>With the <hi>fallen Angels,</hi> that ſin only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods power; thou ſinneſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Grace.</p>
               <p>With <hi>thy ſelf,</hi> What thou ſhouldeſt have been if man had not fallen, what thou art now by ſin, what thou mighteſt have been, if thou hadſt not neglected thy duty.</p>
               <p>With <hi>others</hi> inferiour in <hi>means,</hi> ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in <hi>growth,</hi> that have fewer mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and more thankfulneſs.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:134628:9"/>
               <p>With the Holy <hi>Angels,</hi> who ſerve God chearfully, readily, ſincerely, fervent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, conſtantly.</p>
               <p>With <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Who was meek, and lowly in heart, who for our ſakes humbled himſelf, and was obedient to the death of the Croſs; and then thou wilt abhor thy ſelf in duſt and aſhes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>§. <hi>2.</hi> The beſt Phyſitian.</head>
               <list>
                  <head>Chriſt our heavenly Phyſitian exceeds all earthly Phyſitians in ſeven things.</head>
                  <item>1. He never leaves any work behind him for others.</item>
                  <item>2. He never undertakes any cure, but he finiſheth it.</item>
                  <item>3. He doth all freely, without deſert in us, or reward from us.</item>
                  <item>4. There is nothing in him, but hath a healing vertue in it, his eye, his lips, his hand, his blood, his garments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. He cures Nations as well as Perſons.</item>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:134628:9"/>
                  <item>6. He cures Death as well as Diſeaſes.</item>
                  <item>7. He alwayes makes his Patients the better, not only after, but by their ſickneſs.</item>
               </list>
               <q>
                  <l>Oh! I am ſick of ſin. Lord ſhew thy Art,</l>
                  <l>One touch of thine will break, and heat my heart:</l>
                  <l>O rare Phyſician, that ſhedſt thy blood,</l>
                  <l>And giveſt thy life, to do poor ſinners good.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>§. <hi>3.</hi> Succeſsfull begging.</head>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <head>The way to be heard in prayer, and not to looſe our labour, is,</head>
                     <item>1. To <hi>ask in faith,</hi> Mark 11.24. that is, believing God is able and willing to beſtow good things on us.</item>
                     <item>2. To <hi>ask in ſincerity,</hi> for right ends, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.3.</item>
                     <item>3. To <hi>ask fervently</hi> as <hi>Jacob,</hi> who wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtled with God, and prevailed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.28.</item>
                     <item>4. <hi>Seaſonably,</hi> while the door is open, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.6. <hi>Seek the Lord while he may be found.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:134628:10"/>
                     <item>5. <hi>Conſtantly,</hi> pray continually, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.17. or without ceaſing.</item>
                     <item>6. <hi>Patiently, Pſal.</hi> 40.1.</item>
                  </list>
                  <q>
                     <l>He that can pray to God withall this coſt,</l>
                     <l>Is ſure his labour never ſhall be loſt.</l>
                     <l>Who asks in ſound faith, zeal, fixt patience,</l>
                     <l>And ſeaſon, alwayes, hath ſure recompence.</l>
                     <l>Stay not at one, or two, or four, or five,</l>
                     <l>But get all ſix, and then be ſure thou'lt thrive.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>§. <hi>4.</hi> The Heavenly care. <hi>From Dr.</hi> H.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>There are five things conſiderable in that Promiſe, he careth for you,</hi> 1 Pet. 5.7.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>
                     <hi>There are five things conſiderable in that Promiſe, he careth for you,</hi> 1 Pet. 5.7.</head>
                  <item>1. God cares for his people when they think he doth not.</item>
                  <item>2. He ſo cares for them, as he cares for none elſe comparatively.</item>
                  <item>3. He cares for them, when none elſe care for them.</item>
                  <item>4. He cares for them, when thoſe that ſhould care for them neglect them.</item>
                  <item>5. He cares with others to bleſs their
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:134628:10"/> care, and make it ſucceſsfull.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Q. <hi>But muſt Gods Children caſt off all care?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No, they muſt uſe a care of pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and providence, a Godly care, but they muſt take heed of worldly, immoderate, heart-breaking, heart-corroding, diſtruſting care.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Martha</hi> with many things diſtracts her mind,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mary</hi> in one thing all content doth find.</l>
                  <l>Lord cure my cares, that I thy word may hear;</l>
                  <l>Lord chooſe for me the troubles I ſhall bear.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>§. <hi>5.</hi> The Dutiful Aid.</head>
               <p>God hath in wiſdome ſo framed our bodies, that one part cannot ſay to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I have no need of thee. So it is in the Political; and Eccleſiaſtical body. The Prince cannot ſay to the Subject, he hath no mind of him; nor the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Prince, he hath no need of him; for he is the Miniſter of God to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:134628:11"/> us for good. The like may be ſaid of Miniſters, if they need our Temporals, we need their Spirituals. Know there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that Superiours need the prayers of Inferiours; becauſe</p>
               <p>They reſemble God more then others.</p>
               <p>They have a greater charge lies up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them.</p>
               <p>They have more tentations ſtanding on higher ground.</p>
               <p>They have more influence to do good; they ſet the leſſer wheels in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>They commit more faults, and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſin alone.</p>
               <p>They have more opportunities.</p>
               <p>They muſt give a greater account at the laſt day.</p>
               <p>The beſt aſſiſtance that can be given them by Inferiours, is to pray that the ſpecial preſence of God may be with them. Let inferiours remember theſe things, and it will keep them from envy, murmuring, ambition, reviling, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:134628:11"/>
               <head>§. <hi>6.</hi> Of the Love of God.</head>
               <p>A True Chriſtian loves God no more with the world to boot, then though he were all alone without the World.</p>
               <p>It is God a Chriſtian loves in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and he loves them for God; as the Fiſherman loves the fiſh, for the pearle that is in it.</p>
               <p>He that loves not God above all, loves him not at all. <hi>Joſeph</hi> loves his Miſtriſs, his Maſter, and God; but when his Miſtris's love roſe up againſt his Duty and love to his Maſter, away he runs, as he would have forſaken his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, had it been contrary to God. For a True Chriſtian ſtands alwayes ready to forgo all for the love of God. True love to God is ſincere, ſupream, univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, conſtant.</p>
               <p>Our obedience to Chriſt is a ſure ground of our love to him. <hi>If you love me keep my Commandments,</hi> Joh. 14.15.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:134628:12"/>
               <p>Or love to Chriſt is a ſign. We are beloved of Chriſt, 1 Joh. 4.19.</p>
               <p>From Chriſts love to us ſpring all the bleſſings of time and eternity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <head>§. <hi>7.</hi> A Dialogue between a Miniſter and a Chriſtian.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pray Sir, which is the way to Heaven?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Your ready way lies in the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, which is the King of Heavens high-way.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Which are they?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>The Ordinances of God are,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Word both read by us, and heard from Miniſters.</p>
                  <p>The Duties here to be obſerved are, <hi>before it</hi> Preparation; <hi>at it</hi> Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; <hi>after it</hi> Practiſe.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Sacraments, and ſeals of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, which are,
<list>
                        <item>1. Baptiſm; the type Circumciſion; the duties <hi>going before</hi> it, Prayer; <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:134628:12"/> after,</hi> the care of a new life.</item>
                        <item>2. The Lords Supper; the <hi>Type,</hi> the Paſs-over; duties herein, <hi>going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</hi> examination; <hi>at it,</hi> the uſe of faith to apprehend and apply Chriſt; <hi>after it,</hi> a tryal what benefit we have received, an amendment of life, a care to keep our Covenant with God.</item>
                        <item>3. Prayer, the Key of Heaven; the <hi>type</hi> incenſe. Duties <hi>before it</hi> are, ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and emptying our hearts; <hi>in it,</hi> fervency of Spirit, and Faith; <hi>after it,</hi> care to walk worthy of Mercy, paſt, preſent, future.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Take the Spirit for your guide, you cannot miſs the way; there be no turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to the right hand or the left: Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low your Leader, doubt not. By an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Authour.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <head>§. <hi>8.</hi> How to preſerve Love among Chriſtians.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Avoid groundleſs ſuſpitions, and jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies, which will be the break-neck of true Charity.</item>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:134628:13"/>
                  <item>2. Keep down thy natural paſſions; and in fighting with them, be ſure to watch the firſt riſe of them, and fight with that that thou knoweſt the ſtrongeſt. Paſſions are an unnatural heat, that prey upon brotherly love and charity.</item>
                  <item>3. Be courteous in thy ſalutations. This draws out and ſtrengthens love.</item>
                  <item>4. Bear one anothers infirmities.</item>
                  <item>5. Stand for thy Chriſtian friends, when they be ſpoken againſt.</item>
                  <item>6. Pray for one another heartily.</item>
                  <item>7. Viſit the afflicted in their miſery.</item>
                  <item>8. Hold faſt to the Truth.</item>
                  <item>9. At ſome times part with that which is thy right. Do nothing to make any hate thee; ſuffer ſomething to make them love thee.</item>
                  <item>10. Interpret doubtfull things in the moſt charitable way.</item>
                  <item>11. Take not all advantages for gaine, or opportunities to riſe and get pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment in the world; be contented others ſhould out-ſhine thee.</item>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:134628:13"/>
                  <item>12. Ever remember the three great <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porters of love; Humility</hi> which wins others; <hi>Diligence,</hi> which helps others; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d <hi>quietneſs</hi> which pleaſes others. Be good with quietneſs, do good with chearfulneſs, and receive good with thankfulneſs: This is the way to promote and increaſe love.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <head>§. <hi>9.</hi> The Spiritual Touch-ſtone.</head>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Twelve Graces that diſtinguiſh a true Saint from a counterfeit one:</hi> 
                     </head>
                     <item>1. Brokenneſs of heart for, and from all ſin.</item>
                     <item>2. Mourning for other mens ſins, as <hi>Lot, David, Jeremy, Ezra, Nehemiah, Paul,</hi> did; This is an argument of great ſincerity, for we never read any in Scripture did this but Godly men.</item>
                     <item>3. The grace of ſelf-denyal in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of it, to be able to deny natural, worldly, religious ſelf: this is a grace none but a true Chriſtian can attain to.</item>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:134628:14"/>
                     <item>4. To love God for himſelf, not onely becauſe he is our good, but becauſe he is the chief good; not onely to make our Heaven our God, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o know and believe, God himſelf is our heaven and happineſs.</item>
                     <item>5. To love a child of God, becauſe he is a child of God; and the more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent he is in grace, the more to love him; to love all the Godly as well as ſome, to love their company, and to take their reproofs kindly, is the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing character of a true Saint.</item>
                     <item>6. To advance the Glory of God in thought, word, and deed, and to rejoyce that Chriſt is magnified, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever becomes of us.</item>
                     <item>7. To prize <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> for himſelf, as well as his rewards; to prize his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Propheticall, as well as his Prieſtly Office, to prize him above all things, and at all times, is a ſure note of a child of God.</item>
                     <item>8. Every branch in Chriſt bringeth forth fruit; every true Saint is a growing,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:134628:14"/> and a fruitfull Saint. A picture of a Child doth not grow, but a living Child doth.</item>
                     <item>9. A true Saint is heavenly-minded; his thoughts, his affections, his hope, joy, deſire, his ſpeech, his converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are all heavenly.</item>
                     <item>10. A true Saint is careful to redeem his time. <hi>Natural men make no conſcience</hi> of <hi>idle thoughts, idle words,</hi> and <hi>idle time.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>11. He is known by the Uniformity and univerſality of his obedience to the will of God, he hath reſpect to all Gods Commandments; he is holy and honeſt. A true Chriſtian makes conſcience to abſtain from the ſins of both Tables, and to do the duties of both Tables, that he may keep a conſcience void of offence towards God and Man.</item>
                     <item>12. Every true Saint hath a thankfull heart, a thankfull tongue, and a thankfull life.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:134628:15"/>
               <head>§. <hi>10.</hi> The ſeven laſt words of Chriſt.</head>
               <p>The firſt was a word of mercy for his perſecutors.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Luke <hi>23.34.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Father forgive them they know not what they do.</p>
               </q>
               <p>The ſecond was a word of free-grace to the penitent thief.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Luke <hi>23.43.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>This day ſhalt thou be with me in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe.</p>
               </q>
               <p>The third a word of care and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for his dear Mother.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Joh. <hi>19.26, 27.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Behold thy Son! behold thy Mother.</p>
               </q>
               <p>The fourth a word of ſad complaint.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Mat. <hi>27.46.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</p>
               </q>
               <p>The fifth, a word of want and diſtreſs.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Iohn <hi>19.28.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I thirſt.</p>
               </q>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:134628:15"/>
               <p>The ſixth, a word of triumph and gratulation.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Iohn <hi>19.30.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>It is finiſhed.</p>
               </q>
               <p>The ſeventh, a word of perſeverance.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Luke <hi>23.46.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Father into thy hands I commend my ſpirit.</p>
               </q>
               <div type="section">
                  <list>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Twenty Directions how to live well and dye well from theſe ſeven laſt words of Chriſt, being the heads of ſeveral Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, preached by Mr.</hi> E. C. B. M.</head>
                     <item>1. He that would live well and dye well, muſt be much in prayer. The firſt, fourth, ſeventh words are pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</item>
                     <item>2. He muſt be well verſed in the Book of <hi>Pſalms:</hi> the fourth and ſeventh words are out of it.</item>
                     <item>3. He muſt forgive his Enemies, and pray for them.</item>
                     <item>4. He muſt have a care of relations, and diſpoſe of his worldly eſtate.</item>
                     <item>5. He muſt do what he can to convert others.</item>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:134628:16"/>
                     <item>6. He muſt not abuſe the example of the penitent thief, to delay his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</item>
                     <item>7. He muſt believe the ſouls of the Godly go immediately upon their death to a Heavenly Paradiſe.</item>
                     <item>8. He muſt thirſt after communion with God, and the enjoyment of God in Heaven. <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> thirſted af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our ſalvation.</item>
                     <item>9. He muſt meditate of the ſoul and body ſufferings of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> what he ſuffered in his ſoul, when he ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered the fourth word; what he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in his body when he uttered the fifth word.</item>
                     <item>10. He muſt ſo live, as that he may up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on good grounds <hi>call God Father:</hi> The firſt word was, <hi>Father forgive them:</hi> The laſt word was, <hi>Father in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy hands, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>11. He muſt take more care for hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> precious ſoul, then his mortal body.</item>
                     <item>12. He muſt believe that Chriſt hath finiſhed all things neceſſary for hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="17" facs="tcp:134628:16"/> ſalvation, in point of merit and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, and that nothing is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of him, but to teſtifie his thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs in a holy life.</item>
                     <item>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>3. He muſt believe on good grounds that Chriſt hath finiſhed <hi>His Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> O happy man, that when he is breathing out his laſt, can ſay, <hi>my ſalvation is finiſhed.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>4. He muſt finiſh whatſoever is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, and to be done by him to fit him for heaven; ſomething we are to do, and we muſt finiſh it; not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begin well, but end well.</item>
                     <item>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>5. He muſt fly in the time of tentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Chriſts ſufferings; there is a great deal of comfort in that word <hi>it is finiſhed.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>6. He muſt ſtay himſelf on God in a time of darkneſs when there is no light; Chriſt ſaid, <hi>My God:</hi> we muſt not let go the faith of adherance, though we want the faith of evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</item>
                     <item>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>7. He muſt remember Chriſt wore a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:134628:17"/> Crown of Thorns, that we migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> wear a Crown of Glory; he was for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaken for a time, that we might no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> be forſaken for ever.</item>
                     <item>18. He muſt believe, that through ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny tribulations, we may enter int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the Kingdom of Heaven. A man ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> from the Croſs go to Heaven. Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> was Crucified between two thieve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> and yet died gloriouſly.</item>
                     <item>19. He muſt ſtudy the love of Chriſt i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſuffering ſuch a curſed death on th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Croſs for his ſins, that he may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> able to ſay, <hi>He loved me, and gav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> himſelf for me;</hi> and rejoyce in no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing <hi>ſave in the Croſs of Chriſt.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>20. He muſt after the example of Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> commend his ſoul to Gods hands and remember Chriſt hath commend<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed thy ſoul and my ſoul already int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the hands of God, and when we dy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> God will remember the <hi>depoſitu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> left with him.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:134628:17"/>
               <head>§. <hi>11.</hi> The order a Chriſtian is to obſerve in his walking every day: with an anſwer to objections, and encouragement to ſet about it.</head>
               <p n="1">1. In the morning <hi>awake with God, Pſal.</hi> 139.18. <hi>(i. e.)</hi> ſeaſon thy mind with awful and thankful thoughts of Gods morning and evening mercies, and lift up thy heart in ſome ſhort mental prayer to God, that he would help thee to renew thy reſolution to walk with him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When thou art up, as ſoon as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently thou canſt <hi>betake thy ſelf to prayer.</hi> Private prayer ſhould be the firſt thing we do. The firſt hour is the Golden hour, and by ſo doing thou mayeſt open thy heart to God, and ſhut it againſt all ſin. For family prayer, that is the fitteſt hour, when all the family, or the greateſt part, can moſt conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently meet together; and if thou art a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:134628:18"/> ſervant, take heed of voluntary negle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cting family prayer: Let it be ſome ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent occaſion that hinders thee, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> when thou canſt not be there with thy bodily preſence, yet be ſure thy affecti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on be with them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. After prayer, and other religiou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> duties performed, <hi>Go to thy calling, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> follow the works thereof,</hi> (as that ſtatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God hath ſet thee in) <hi>with diligence, conſcience and chearfulneſs,</hi> and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with thy calling though mean. Be not like worldlings, who do all with a greedy mind of getting: But remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber a Chriſtian hath two Callings, one general, the other particular; and he is a happy and wiſe ſervant that ſo minds his general, as not to neglect his parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, and ſo follows his particular Call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as he doth not neglect his general: Uſually the former have ſome tincture of hypocriſie, and the latter are too much over-grown with covetouſneſs. Labour therefore to keep thy eye upon thy heart, and upon the rule. Do all in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:134628:18"/> thy particular Calling with uprightneſs and faithfulneſs, in wiſdom and order, referring the ſucceſs to Gods bleſſing, and labour to be armed with patience againſt croſſes and loſſes. In buying and ſelling, take heed of lying and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation, covetouſneſs and froward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, of multiplying words careleſly, and of over-praiſing thy own wares when thou ſelleſt, and ſaying <hi>it is naught when thou buyeſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. When <hi>thou art alone</hi> look to thy heart, and ſay, Heart, where art thou? what art thou doing? where haſt thou been? whither art thou going? keep thy heart with all diligence; <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.23. Keep it as a Guardian would do a rich Heir, that hath many Suitors, or as a General would do a Caſtle that was a key or in-let to the whole Country; and in order to this remember five things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Obſerve the motions of it; thy mind is thy ſelf. Be not a ſtranger to thy ſelf; God looks at the heart, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.7. he delights in truth in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.6.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:134628:19"/>2. When any good thoughts and holy motions come into thy ſoul (as thoſe that are truly good ſhall not find themſelves long without them) cheriſh and entertain them; ſay as the Spouſe, <hi>It is the voice of my beloved that knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth;</hi> ſay, <hi>Come in thou bleſſed of the Lord,</hi> why ſtandeſt thou without? but i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> evil motions ariſe, let them not lodge with thee, but <hi>chaſe them from thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Employ thy heart, and ſet it t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> work. The mind is a reſtleſs mill, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in motion. <hi>Calvin</hi> prayed every day, the devil might never find him idle If our hearts be doing nothing, they will be doing evil; like a garden, if yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> do not ſow good ſeeds, will ſoon b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> overun with weeds. Remember, <hi>Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and Nature abhor idleneſs,</hi> and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil watches <hi>for the idle hour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Limit the workings of thy ſoul that the world may have no more o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thy thoughts and time then needs muſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Spiritualize the operations of thy mind, and extract heavenly and divin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:134628:19"/> meditations out of thy employments, out of fit objects.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Look carefully to thy ſenſes,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially make a Covenant with thy eyes, as <hi>Job</hi> did Chap. 31.1. and pray with <hi>David,</hi> that God would turn away thy eyes from beholding vanity, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.37. There is a quick paſſage from the eye to the heart. A Chriſtian ſhould not let his eyes fly at random. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der:</p>
               <p n="1">1. The eye is a ſenſe of the greateſt extent and latitude; it beholds all on earth, and reaches even to heaven.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is a ſenſe above all others moſt frequently and conſtantly exerciſed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It works more immediately and ſtrongly upon the heart and fancy.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It is a ſenſe above all others moſt eaſily induced to ſin, to wantonneſs and vanity, to injuſtice and oppreſſion, to covetouſneſs and idolatry: Pride and Envy dwell in the eye, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 23.16. <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.33. <hi>Jer.</hi> 22.17. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 7.21. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 6.9. <hi>Ch.</hi> 20.24.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:134628:20"/>5. It is a moſt noble Senſe, God hath provided noble objects for it; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore O Chriſtian, young or old, look t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thy eyes every day, give not indulgenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and liberty to them. There is a promiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> made to this, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.15. he that ſhut his eyes from ſeeing evil ſhall not dwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with everlaſting burning. Remembe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gods eye is alwayes upon thee; and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that rules his heart, will eaſily rule hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eys; &amp; he that doth not look to his eye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it is a great ſign he never looked well t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his heart. Heaven it ſelf is reſerved fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the eye; hearing is ſuited to faith, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the eye is ſuited for viſion.</p>
               <p n="6">6. If <hi>thou art in company take heed t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thy ſelf,</hi> that if thou canſt do no good nor get no good, thou mayſt do no har<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nor get no harm. If thou at any tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> falleſt into ſuch company, as there is n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> likelihood to do or receive good, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> buſineſs being diſpatched, and civilit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> obſerved, get out of that company, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he cannot be a Chriſtian indeed that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not curious of his company. When tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:134628:20"/> haſt conference with others, ſpeak nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>falſly, raſhly, nor vainly,</hi> let thy words be <hi>few, true, ſpiritual;</hi> let no fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy communication come out of your mouth: Let thy ſpeech be alwayes gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, ſeaſoned with ſalt, ſuch as may miniſter grace to the hearers. Speak of God, his Word, Works, Ordinances <hi>with holy reverence.</hi> Speak of thy ſelf <hi>modeſtly and humbly,</hi> of others <hi>chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably;</hi> of the gifts and graces of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>with joy and thankfulneſs;</hi> of the infirmities and failings of good men <hi>ſpeak ſparingly,</hi> and with a due <hi>reſpect to their good name:</hi> Of the ſins of wicked men, ſpeak not but <hi>with grief and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation,</hi> and <hi>admiration of the grace of God to thee,</hi> ſince what is in their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, is in thy nature, and who is it O man makes thee to differ? It may be uſefull and neceſſary to ſpeak of the world and civil things: But let not theſe things take up all thy talk. If thou enquireſt after news, let it be to underſtand how it goes with Gods
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:134628:21"/> Church, that thou mayeſt the better di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect thy prayers for them if afflicted, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thy praiſes if they proſper: Specially take heed of the ſins of theſe times <hi>much ſpeaking, raſh cenſuring, prou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> boaſting, ſlandering and backbiting, ſpeaking evil of dignities, ſpreading falſe reports,</hi> which are too much the ſins of profeſſors; as <hi>prophane ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, horrible imprecations and curſings, ſordid flattery, obſcene talking, ſcoffing</hi> and <hi>mocking at Piety</hi> are the ſins of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors and Ranters.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Wherever thou art, <hi>at home or abroad, give good examples,</hi> that thou mayſt not leave any ſtinking ſavour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind thee, to open the mouths of the malicious, to harden them in their ſins, and make the weak to ſtumble, or to ſad the hearts of the Godly. We may be innocently chearful in company, and in a journey, to paſs over the weariſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the way: but let thy modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be known to all, be not prophane, idle, vain, eſpecially take heed to thy
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:134628:21"/> words and actions <hi>before Children.</hi> For the heathen could ſay, <hi>there is a great reverence due to them;</hi> the ſeeds of goodneſs are ſoon quenched, and viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous inclinations are more corroborated. Let it be then thy great care in all thy wayes and actions, to ſhew thy ſelf a pattern of goodneſs, labouring to adorn the Goſpel of Chriſt, holding forth the word of life in a good converſation; to which purpoſe make it thy care to walk in the exerciſe of four things;</p>
               <p n="1">1. To ſhew <hi>all fidelity and honeſty in thy dealings.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> would have us to have our converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on honeſt among the Gentiles, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.12. It is a vain thing to pretend to be religious if we be not honeſt. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> would have poor Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, to ſhew all good fidelity, that they may adorn the Goſpel of our <hi>Lord Jeſus,</hi> 2 <hi>Tit.</hi> 10. It is a wofull time, when we know not where to find <hi>a faithfull man.</hi> God forbid it ſhould be ſaid, that Turks, and ſome Papiſts, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:134628:22"/> Quakers, and common Proteſtants have more uprightneſs, truth and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in their words and dealings, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thoſe that make the higheſt profeſſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in Religion. By theſe ſins God ſuffers i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his honour, Jeſus Chriſt ſuffers, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Goſpel ſuffers, and the Godly ſuffer. By being faithful in your dealings, you will beat the enemies of Chriſtianity with their own weapons; all the Glory they have is their juſtice and fidelity, that they wrong no man, that they will not circumvent and work upon their neighbours neceſſity or ignorance. Now when a Chriſtian ſhews ſuch fidelity, he overcomes them in that which they themſelves confeſs to be good; and all men ſee, that if there be any thing in them praiſe-worthy, it is to be found among true Chriſtians with more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage and luſtre.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Labour to evidence an humble ſubjection to thoſe in Authority over us. This is the <hi>Herculean</hi> Argument the Papiſts and other wicked men uſe in all
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:134628:22"/> ages againſt the Godly, That they are enemies to Kings, ſtubborn, diſobedient, turning all things upſide down. It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes then all that profeſs the name of Chriſt, as far as they can to obey all the commands of Magiſtrates; for this is the will of God, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.1. and to give <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll lawfull demonſtrations, that we are not ſtubborn, refractory perſons; That if any do maliciouſly accuſe us, we may be able to ſay with <hi>Daniel,</hi> that inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency is found in us before God, and that to the King we have done no hurt, <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.22.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thou muſt labour for a peaceable converſation, avoiding as much as you can all contentions and quarrels, ſtudy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng to be quiet, and minding your own buſineſs, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.11. remembring the Apoſtles rules, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14. follow peace with all men, and holineſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As much in you lyes live peaceably with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll men, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.18. (have peace, keep peace, love peace, make peace, ſeek peace; that phraſe, <hi>live peaceably,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:134628:23"/> all.) That ſo the wicked may ſay of us, as the <hi>Shechemites</hi> of <hi>Jacob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Sons,</hi> Theſe men are peaceable with us therefore let them dwell in the land, <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.21. It is a queſtion yet unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, whether the perſecutions o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> enemies, or the diviſions of brethren have done the Church of God mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> harm.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Thou muſt walk charitably: la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour after a beneficialneſs in thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, to be profitable to men, to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> publick ſpirited, open handed to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> poor, to be as <hi>Job</hi> was, eyes to the blind to cloath the naked, viſit the ſick, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the fatherleſs and widow. This i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> well pleaſing to God; theſe things ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> good and profitable to men.</p>
               <p>This is the way to adorn thy Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, and to be a pattern of goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> works; and without ſuch things as theſe thy profeſſion and religious perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances will have no great luſtre no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> beauty.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:134628:23"/>8. If God <hi>give thee proſperity, and riches increaſe, be not overjoyed with it.</hi> Truſt not in uncertain riches, do not bleſs thy ſelf in abundance, as if thy happineſs did ſtand in poſſeſſing, or thou wert ſure to have theſe things continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. If we rejoyce exceedingly in the day of proſperity, we ſhall grieve im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderately when the time of parting comes.</p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>Therefore prepare for adverſity.</hi> Thy Saviour hath commanded thee to take up thy Croſs daily, in preparation and expectation; And <hi>Solomon</hi> hath told us, <hi>We know not what a day may bring forth.</hi> If adverſity comes, be not impatient; murmur not againſt God, if he cut ſhort thy Eſtate, but ſay with holy <hi>Job, Shall I receive good things at Gods hand and not evil? The Lord gives, and the Lord takes, bleſſed be his holy Name,</hi> Job 1.21. <hi>c.</hi> 2.10.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>In Recreations which the neceſſity of Nature calls for, and Religion doth not deny:</hi> Look to thy ſelf, for it is eaſie
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:134628:24"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:134628:24"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:134628:25"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:134628:25"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:134628:26"/> ſtepping out of the uſe into the abuſe of them; See therefore,
<list>
                     <item>1. To the kind of them, that they be lawful, innocent, and of good report, as alſo that thy recreations be in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive: That which is in it ſelf lawfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> may be in expedient. Uſe no recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that hath got an univerſal evi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> report among Sober, Godly, Wiſe grave perſons.</item>
                     <item>2. To the time. We ſhould abridge ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſelves Recreations in times of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Calamity to our Country, or th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Church of God. See alſo that it b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> not on the Lords day, which is to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> employed in Heavenly exerciſe. W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> muſt not ſuffer them to thruſt out Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily duties, or croud them up in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> narrow compaſs: And finally, ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> that they take thee not off from the important works of thy Calling.</item>
                     <item>3. To the place, that it be not too pub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lick and open to draw others to ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> us, who notwithſtanding thy libert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> may be offended; or that it be not
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:134628:26"/> place of guſling and drinking, where we may be drawn to exceſs.</item>
                     <item>4. To thy Company, that we ſort our our ſelves as much as we can with Godly, wiſe Chriſtians.</item>
                     <item>5. In the continuance of them. Recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as they ſhould not be over fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, ſo they ſhould not be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long. Make not thy <hi>by-work, thy work;</hi> Uſe them as ſauce, a little here is enough, and enough may be too much; and as the Proverb ſaith, <hi>Too much of one thing is good for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>6. To the end of them, which muſt be to refreſh the outward man, to bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit the inward man. We muſt not play to play. No man uſes a whet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, but to put a keenneſs upon an Inſtrument. Imitate the Primitive Chriſtians, of whom <hi>Tertullian</hi> gives this account: <hi>We ſit not down to eat, till we have firſt prayed to God; we eat ſo as to ſatisfie hunger; we drink ſo as not to enflame luſt; we feaſt ſo, as
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:134628:27"/> to remember we muſt go to prayer, and come away as if we had been at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> watch, rather then a feaſt.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>Be ready to every good work,</hi> and conſtantly perform ſuch holy dutie as God calls thee to, and do not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly omit them. If God calls thee to hear his word, and pray to him, go to it that not out of form, but out of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of thy duty, and a ſenſe of thy wants; get ſome time every day fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Meditation of Gods <hi>Word and Works</hi> and if thou art ſo barren, thou canſt no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> find matter, meditate of thy barrenneſs, and humble thy ſoul for it.</p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>And now in the Evening, take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> view of the former particulars,</hi> and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine all; <hi>how thou haſt prayed,</hi> how <hi>thou haſt performed the works of thy Calling,</hi> what hath <hi>come into thy thoughts,</hi> what hath gone <hi>out of thy mouth,</hi> how <hi>thou doſt find thy ſelf in proſperity and adverſity,</hi> how it <hi>hath been with thee at home, and abroad, alone,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:134628:27"/> and in company, in recreations, and in religious duties:</hi> And herein deal faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully with thy own ſoul. If thou haſt upon due enquiry into thy ſelf found, that thou haſt kept this order in ſome good manner, give God the praiſe and Glory: If thou be conſcious to thy ſelf of any diſorder, blame and ſhame thy ſelf, beg pardon of God, fly to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Chriſt, renew thy reſolutions to walk with more watchfulneſs. And as thou didſt riſe with God in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſo cloſe the day with him, making thy peace with him, that thou mayſt reſt in the arms of thy beloved, and have good hope thou ſhalt go to heaven, if thou ſhould'ſt dye before the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <div type="objections_and_answers">
                  <head>Objections againſt this daily order in our Converſation.</head>
                  <p>Obj. 1. <hi>O but ſaith the fleſh, this is more</hi> then needs, more then God requires.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> But go and learn what that means,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:134628:28"/> to <hi>love the Lord with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoul, and with all thy mind, and with all thy ſtrength,</hi> and then thou wilt not ſay it is more then needs, except thou thinkeſt there is no need to pleaſe God.</p>
                  <p>Obj. 2. <hi>But this will</hi> ſpoil all mirth <hi>to obſerve this order.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is nothing ſo, theſe Rules ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved will keep from nothing that is lawful, delightful, profitable, thou mayeſt eat, drink, buy, ſell, keep company, recreate thy ſelf, onely it teaches thee to do theſe things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin. If there be no mirth but in ſin, then the Devil is the merrieſt creature in the world, for he doth nothing but ſin.</p>
                  <p>Obj. 3. <hi>But it is impoſſible</hi> to do this alwayes, <hi>and this makes Religion a bondage.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> The love of God makes his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments not to be grievous when we firſt enter on it, it ſeems harſh and hard, not that it is ſo, but it ſeems ſo,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:134628:28"/> becauſe we have uſed our ſelves to ſo much liberty; as a new garment is ſtrait at the firſt putting on, but after a little wearing it is eaſie. Do not ſay Chriſts yoke is heavy and ſtrait, when he ſaith, it is eaſie. If God give thee a new heart, thou wilt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver complain of the difficulty of a new life.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The encouragements to obſerve this Order are theſe five:</head>
                  <p n="1">1. This will keep out many ſins that overtake us for want of it. The reſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt ſin in the morning, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to God to ſtrengthen that reſolution, are excellent helps to keep us from ſin.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It will preſerve us from many troubles and ſorrows, which it doth by keeping us from ſin, for <hi>Sorrow follows ſin, as the ſhadow doth the body.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. It preſerves from lying and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing in ſin; he that obſerves this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:134628:29"/> if he falls in the day through infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, he riſes the ſame day by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and evens his recknings with God through the mediation of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. It will keep us from foul and hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous ſins, from conſcience-waſting ſins, which a man falls not ordinarily into, but by degrees leſſening his care, and remitting in his duty, as we ſee in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> and <hi>Solomon.</hi> The obſerving this daily order, ſtops the diſeaſe in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, quenches the fire in the ſpark, kills the Serpent in the Egg.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. It makes a mans life very comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and joyfull. The more carefully and conſtantly a man walks with God, the more peace and joy he will find and retain. By this means we ſhall be <hi>more fit for holy duties,</hi> and to <hi>perform them in a right manner;</hi> hereby we ſhal the more <hi>eaſily prepare our ſelves for a holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</hi> By this way alſo we ſhall with more ſucceſs <hi>manage our ſpiritual Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict,</hi> even to triumph over Satan. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:134628:29"/> we ſhall <hi>realize the profeſſion of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> we have been ſo ſolemnly dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to in our baptiſm. Laſtly, hereby we are fit <hi>to live in all times,</hi> and thus living we <hi>ſhall be fit to dye.</hi> What need he that hath thus orderly walked with God fear Death, ſince he knows he goes to that God with whom he is at peace?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <head>§. <hi>12.</hi> A Direction to Chriſtians how to carry themſelves in Evil dayes, eſpecially in in times of fear and danger.</head>
               <p n="1">1. It highly concerns every man to <hi>examine and prove himſelf whether he be in the Faith or no,</hi> how the caſe ſtands between God and him, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.40. <hi>Hag.</hi> 1.5. If we will not try our ſelves we ſhall be tryed; and wo unto us, if we be found too light.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We ſhould be every day <hi>weaning our hearts from the world.</hi> Things that hang on a pin eaſily fall off, but things that are glued, are hardly ſevered: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:134628:30"/> love to any worldly thing, makes the croſs ten times heavier; and it is like a heavy burthen on a ſore back. Let not thy heart ſo cleave to theſe things, that judgements ſhould rend and tear them from thee; but let thy affections be ſo mortified, that they may fall off eaſily, as <hi>Elijahs</hi> man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, when he went up to Heaven.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Be <hi>twice as much exerciſed in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Duties as before.</hi> When <hi>Judas</hi> was plotting, Chriſt went to the Paſsover. When <hi>Haman</hi> was revelling, <hi>Eſther</hi> with her Maids were praying. It is good to be well employed, when God is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding circuit in his judgements. Bleſſed is that Servant, who when his Lord comes is found ſo doing.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Labour to keep a good Conſcience;</hi> that though thou haſt trouble without thou mayeſt have peace within. No com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort like a good conſcience, it is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual feaſt; it is like that good Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.12. It will do thee good and not evil all thy dayes: no torment
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:134628:30"/> like a bad one, for it is like that evil Woman, <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.13. that is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual dropping, but drops faſteſt in a rainy day.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Inure thy ſelf to ſome hardineſs.</hi> Delicate perſons can hardly ſuffer. Soft fleſh if it be pinched ſoon ſwells. They that know not how to lay aſide their faſhions, how will they endure the want of the neceſſities of Nature? We ſhould therefore deny our ſelves ſomewhat in meat, drink and apparel, and pleaſures, and abaſe our ſelves, leaſt the Lord abaſe us.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Make ſure of the favour of God.</hi> It will be very ſad to have God and man againſt us both at once. The wrath of a King is like the roaring of a Lion: But who knows the power of Gods an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger?</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Make much of the Promiſes,</hi> and get them in thy heart, and labour to have them in a readineſs upon all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. Thy word, ſaith <hi>David,</hi> hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted me in my affliction. God uſes
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:134628:31"/> more words in promiſes then in any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of his will; when he threatens he ſpeaks ſhortly, when he promiſes he ſpeaks largely.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Get into thy heart the <hi>ſound and experimental knowledge of the Truth,</hi> and a fervent love to it. It is the truth that thou art like to ſuffer for, and a man can never ſuffer for that he doth not know, much leſs for that he doth not love.</p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>Labour to better thy Knowledge in the Doctrine of Afflictions;</hi> to know the nature, uſefulneſs, end of them, how to judge rightly of them, how to bear them, how to improve them: fix in thy mind ſuch things as theſe; <hi>There is no Son of God without Chaſtiſement;</hi> That <hi>no Affliction comes but by the will of God;</hi> That by <hi>Afflictions we are made both ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable and conformable to Chriſt;</hi> That <hi>all troubles, loſſes, ſtrokes are propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned to our ſtrength,</hi> that they all are for <hi>our profit and good:</hi> the more we believe theſe things, the more comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:134628:31"/> and couragious we ſhall be in evil dayes.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Chriſtians ſhould by holy confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nce edifie and comfort one another, Mal.</hi> 3.16. They ſhould improve the communion of Saints, for inſtructing, ſtrengthning; encouraging one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>Meditate often of the attributes of God, the former experiences of Gods dealing with his people,</hi> and the <hi>joyes of heaven,</hi> and the <hi>reward is ſet before us:</hi> as Chriſt did, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1. as <hi>Moſes</hi> did, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.27. and <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 8.18. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17.</p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>Spare no ſin unmortified;</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain no <hi>Dalilah,</hi> no <hi>Herodias,</hi> for in an evil day it will work more woe and bitterneſs then we are aware of. It will fill thee with tormenting fears, and rack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing doubts. One fire-ball will burn thy houſe: one ſin unrepented of will burn thy ſoul. Do not hide iniquity in thy heart, when God is making inquiſition for it.</p>
               <p n="13">
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:134628:32"/>13. <hi>In an evil time the prudent ſhoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> keep ſilence.</hi> There is a time to ſpeak and a time to be ſilent. Many times ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſpeaking diſhonours God, gratifies ene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mies, diſcovers corruption, diſcredits re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligion, endangers our perſons: W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould therefore pray to God to ſet watch before our lips, eſpecially in ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> times, and endeavour our words may be few, true, and ſpiritual.</p>
               <p n="14">14. But we <hi>must not be ſilent as t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> God, in ceaſing to pray unto him,</hi> for i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is his Command, Call upon me in the day of trouble; and he expects whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his chaſtning is upon us, we ſhould pou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> out our prayer unto him, and that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> affliction we ſhould ſeek him early; tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we ſhould pray oftner and better. The nearer Chriſt came to his ſuffering, the more earneſtly he prayed. Go then and enter into thy Chamber, and ſhut thy door; Get under the wings of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, and ſay with <hi>David, Thou art my hiding place,</hi> Pſal. 32.7. <hi>I fly unto thee Lord to hide me,</hi> Pſal. 143.9.</p>
               <p n="15">
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:134628:32"/>15. With other <hi>exerciſes of piety joyn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>harity; exerciſe mercy, forgive thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nemies, be reconciled to thy brethren.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſit the ſick and impriſoned, plead the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>auſe of the widow, give a portion to even, and alſo to eight, for thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt not what evil ſhall be upon the earth, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ccleſ.</hi> 11.2. Therefore, <hi>ſaith the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tous heart,</hi> part with nothing, hoard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p againſt a rainy day; therefore <hi>ſaith God, give freely,</hi> for the merciful ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd mercy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly, let the preſent fears alarum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ee to prepare for ſad events;</hi> go not without thy armour, be not ſecure, ſay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot the over-flowing ſcourge ſhall not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome nigh me. But think with thy ſelf, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hough I have been in the rear of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther judgements, I may be in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ront of this. Labour to be fitted to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ertain terrible things. When thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eareſt the Miniſter ſound the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, and ſay judgement is at hand, the Lord is riſen out of his holy place to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udge the inhabitants of the earth.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:134628:33"/> When thou heareſt what is done to o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers, when wickedneſs is advanced and Godlineſs ſlighted and oppoſed then get thoſe Graces that will fit the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for an evil day: ſuch as,
<list>
                     <item>1. Reſignation of thy ſelf, and all tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> haſt unto God; be content that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſhould diſpoſe of thee as he plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.26.</item>
                     <item>2. Faith, which is a Grace will live i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> hard times, for Faith lays claim to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> fulneſs of Chriſt <hi>as its own.</hi> Fait<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> hath two hands, a working hand an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> a receiving hand, the receiving han<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> relieves the working hand.</item>
                     <item>3. Apply the promiſes of perſeverance</item>
                     <item>4. Patience in both its Acts, the bear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing act, and the waiting act, and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> doing, thou mayeſt be able to ſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in the evil day; <hi>Which none of theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> five ſorts of men will be able to do.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>1. They that ſlight God and Religio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in peace and proſperity, will neve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſuffer for God and Religion in ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>verſity.</item>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:134628:33"/>
                     <item>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Thoſe that will not witneſs for truth with their mouths, will never for the truths ſake lay down their lives.</item>
                     <item>3. Thoſe that ſerve God onely for the praiſe of men, will leave the ſervice of God when men diſgrace them.</item>
                     <item>4. Thoſe that will not endure the ſmaller tryals, will much leſs ſtand in the greater.</item>
                     <item>5. They that will not ſuffer the power of Gods word to part them and their luſts, and vain converſation, will not ſeal the truth of Gods word with their blood.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="part">
               <head>§. <hi>13.</hi> A few Motives to young perſons to be Religious.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>here was never more need for <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, Parents, Tutors, Maſters,</hi> to ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon youth with piety, and to improve <hi>their intereſt, wiſdom, authority in this</hi> Work, then in theſe days, wherein there
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:134628:34"/> is ſuch a general decay of Godlineſs, that if God do not ſtir up the hearts of Governours, and if they will not ſtir up themſelves, and thoſe under their charge, the next Generation are like to prove Banquerupts in Religion, and to prove either Papiſts or Atheiſts. To en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage young perſons to look to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to call them out of the tent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of wickedneſs;, I would earneſtly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat them to let theſe few conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons reſt upon their minds.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>O young man or young woman, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the end of thy being,</hi> Why God made thee, and gave thee a reaſonabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſoul, capable of eternal happineſs? why did God beſtow upon thee many en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments of mind and body? why he hath vouchſafed the cultivation and improvement of thy natural abilities by education and inſtruction? Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> all this that thou mighteſt glorifie him, and be ſerviceable in thy Generation to the great end of being and living? Canſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thou imagine that ſo bright a lamp as a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:134628:34"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mmortal ſoul, was ever put into the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arthen candleſtick of thy body, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſe and ſenſual ends, meerly to ſerve <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y fleſhly appetite, the moſt deformed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd unſatiable monſter that is in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orld? Canſt thou upon ſerious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oughts conceive thy being is for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch poor low ends? No, remember <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od and men expect better things from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee. You that are young, the good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d welfare of Church and State de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ends on you: you are the <hi>Seed-plots <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d Nurſeries of all Religion and Vertue, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Liberty, Honour, Trade;</hi> either you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſt tranſmit, and hand theſe down to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſterity, or all theſe muſt dye and be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xtinguiſhed in your hands; and are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou willing to be recorded in future <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſtories for prodigals and betrayers of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem all? Such a man by Religion and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ertue raiſed his Family; and ſuch an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eir, ſuch a Grand-child ruined it by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is debauchery. <hi>Stobeus</hi> relates, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he <hi>Ephebi</hi> among the <hi>Athenians</hi> took <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Oath, not to leave their Country in
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:134628:35"/> a worſe condition then they found i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but in a better: Oh that it might be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſaid of this Generation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Conſider, <hi>It is a monſtrous thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for young perſons to be old ſinners.</hi> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Age in which ſin is committed is ſo f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from excuſing it, that it aggravates it. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is a ſad character of a man, he <hi>was ſo a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſo wicked of a Child;</hi> he was a ſweare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a lyar, a ſcoffer, an enemy to Godline<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>from his long Coates.</hi> God himſelf wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he would aggravate mans ſin, ſaith, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> imaginations of mans heart hath be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> evil from his youth, <hi>Gen.</hi> 8.21. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> in his Confeſſions bewails h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> boyiſh tricks, Lord, when I was a litt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Boy I was a great ſinner. And <hi>Davi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> begs pardon for the ſins of his youth <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.7. and mark how God brand the diſobedience of <hi>Iſrael, Jer.</hi> 22.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>I ſpake unto thee in thy proſperity, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thou ſaideſt I will not hear; this has been thy manner from thy youth,</hi> tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thou obeydſt not my voice. And in <hi>Jer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 32.30. God aggravates the ſin of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rael</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:134628:35"/> and <hi>Judah,</hi> that they had done evil before him from their youth. Take heed of calling <hi>ſin, tricks of youth,</hi> and and thinking your age gives you a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation. If ever you return to God, thoſe ſins muſt be repented of, and they will coſt you dear; as you may ſee in thoſe Converts, <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.25. <hi>We lye down in our ſhame, and our confuſion covereth us,</hi> for we have ſinned againſt the Lord, we and <hi>our fathers from our Youth even to this day.</hi> Conſider therefore how dear you muſt pay for your youthful luſts, they will prove dear bought plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, they are but honey licked off from thorns: Like that fruit in the <hi>Weſt Indies,</hi> the <hi>Spaniards</hi> call the <hi>Devils ſweet meat;</hi> a fruit very delicious, but the place where it grows is ſo hot in the day, and ſo infeſted with venemous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſects in the night, that none care for dwelling near them. Your youthful pleaſures expoſe you to the ſcorchings of Gods wrath, to the bitings and ſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of your own conſcience. Your
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:134628:36"/> youthful luſts muſt be repented of ei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther here or in hell, where repentanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will do you no good. Conſider wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>theſe</hi> courſes are, none can prevail wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you now to leave, and whither they tend; they provoke God to hate you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> good men are grieved for you, and a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhamed of you, nay, even wicked me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> themſelves in their cool thoughts would not have their children as bad a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> themſelves. But O how few perſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conſider, that by youthful luſts, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lay a foundation for old age miſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ries.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Conſider it is the greateſt honou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to be good betimes.</hi> It was the praiſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that good Courtier <hi>Obadiah,</hi> he feare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Lord from his youth. It was the Glory of <hi>Joſiah,</hi> that while <hi>he was ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> young</hi> he began to ſeek after the God o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>David</hi> his father, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.3. It wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the commendation of <hi>Timothy,</hi> tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from a child he had known the Holy Scriptures, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. God takes i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> very kindly when you begin betimes to
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:134628:36"/> ſerve him, <hi>Cant.</hi> 7.12. Chriſt <hi>loves the buds, the bloſſomings of Grace, as well as the ripe fruit;</hi> and the Devil is a great enemy to this age, he oppoſes the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing young perſons to Chriſt to be dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated and to be inſtructed and catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. There are four reaſons among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers why the Devil labours to corrupt youth.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe he knows a vicious youth layes the foundation of a vicious life. Reaſon teaches, that if we would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the diſpoſition of any thing, we muſt do it while it is young: Now the Devil acts according to this princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and becauſe youth is an age of fancy, and apt to receive impreſſions, therefore he labours to ſtain and pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute it: no colour holds ſo well, as that which is dyed in the wool.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe their age being leaſt able to diſcern between good and evil, will ſooneſt bite at his baits, and yield to his temptations. Young perſons
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:134628:37"/> are ſooneſt catched in his ſnare.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He doth not know how ſhort a time they have to live, and therefore he would get them into his clutches as ſoon as he can.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Becauſe God loves this age, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he loves to be cropping early buds; indeed God highly values a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a Religious Child-hood and youth, he hath given us all teſtimonies how much he accepts it. Under the Law, the acceptable ſervices were <hi>young things,</hi> young lambs, young bullocks, young pigeons; <hi>the firſt ripe fruits, the firſt born,</hi> God challenged to be his. O how doth God delight in young <hi>Samuels,</hi> young <hi>Davids,</hi> young <hi>Daniels,</hi> young <hi>Johns;</hi> the one was a young Prophet, the other a young Apoſtle. Saith God, When <hi>Iſrael</hi> was a Child then I loved him: And can there be a greater honour to you, then to ſay, I loved God from my Child-hood, I knew Chriſt from my Child-hood? to ſay as <hi>David, Pſal.</hi>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:134628:37"/> 71.5. <hi>O Lord I have truſted in thee from my youth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>The word of God doth concern you, and Religion is as proper and fit</hi> for you as for any perſons whatſoever.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Scriptures are written for young perſons,</hi> that they may know how to cleanſe their wayes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.9. The word is <hi>the beſt ſtaff for old men</hi> to lean on, and <hi>the beſt ſword for young men to fight withall.</hi> The Heathens in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed thought, that youth might be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulged in ſin. <hi>Cicero</hi> in his defence of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aelius,</hi> ſaith, ſomething is to be <hi>allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to youth,</hi> till <hi>the heat of that age be abated;</hi> but I could appeal from him as a <hi>Mercenary Oratour</hi> pleading for his Fee the Cauſe of a debauched young man, to himſelf in another place in his ſober mind, telling us, <hi>That this age is in a ſpeciall manner to be kept from luſt,</hi> and that they are much miſtaken, <hi>that think way ſhould be given to the licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſneſs of</hi> young men. But it is no great matter what they thought; ſince we
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:134628:38"/> know God hath ſo framd the Scriptures that Religion belongs not only to thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of riper years, but to Children alſo, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.29. Thoſe words as the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed obſerve have extraordinary point<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the Hebrew, and three times there are mention made of Children in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Decalogue.</hi> The Scripture teaches, ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is a duty you owe to God, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.1. There is a duty you owe to men, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.1. and both theſe are clear, becauſe God hath appointed correction, as a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> means to keep them in the way of thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> duty, <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.15. and God promiſes a <hi>bleſſing</hi> to it, <hi>Pr.</hi> 23.13. now <hi>God</hi> promiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not a bleſſing, but as a means appointe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by him to an end. Nor is there any ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more proper for Religion then this is This the learning age: now you hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> leaſure, now your minds are not ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingaged and prejudiced as they will b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hereafter. Religion is like water, fit to be poured upon tender plants. You will never have a fitter time in your lives. The time of youth is the faireſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:134628:38"/> flower that grows upon the ſtalk of Time. Now your underſtandings are quick, your memories tenacious, your affections ſoft and pliable. If you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem not this time for God and your ſouls, I dare be bold to ſay, you will repent of it ſometime before you dye.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Converſion after youth proves very difficult and rare.</hi> I would not be thought ſo arrogant, as to ſet any bounds to Gods Grace, or limit it to any time. Poſſibly ſome unwary expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions that way have done much harm: But this I ſay, ſins of youth are <hi>hardly left,</hi> and <hi>ſeldom forſaken;</hi> as thoſe bones that grow crooked in Childhood, are hardly rectified when we become men. It is ſaid, <hi>Mark</hi> 11.13. the time of figs <hi>was not yet;</hi> the time of gathering figs was not yet, as ſome expound that place, it was a time of bearing figs, for that kind of fig tree, <hi>ſaith a learned man,</hi> uſes to have fruit on it of the firſt, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and third years growth: Now Chriſt being hungry came to ſee if he
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:134628:39"/> could find <hi>any thing</hi> upon it. Old age i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the time of gathering fruit; Youth i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the time of bearing fruit. If you do no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bear fruit while you are young, how ſhall Chriſt gather fruit when you are old? and what then can you look fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but a curſe?</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Good education makes the ſins of youth more heynous.</hi> You therefore that have ſprang from Godly Parents, that have been the Children of many pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and tears; you that have been brought up in Godly Families, that have had <hi>many Fathers, many Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors,</hi> know you cannot ſin at ſo eaſie a rate as others. And here I cannot but take up a ſad lamentation over the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate children of Godly parents and anceſtours; Then which there is not a worſe ſymptome among us of Gods ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter leaving and forſaking us: Many Sons and Daughters are ſo given over to looſeneſs, prodigality, ſcurrility, pride, uncleanneſs, contempt both of the form and power of Religion, that if their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:134628:39"/> and Anceſtours were now upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arth, would they know them to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eir Poſterity? Surely it may be ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f them, as in the Prophet, <hi>Abraham is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gnorant of them, and Iſrael knows them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot. Sarah,</hi> and thoſe <hi>Holy Women of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ld,</hi> would not know their Daughters. Thoſe Squirril-brain'd creatures that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>isk from one faſhion to another; thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>potted and painted faces of yours, do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore reſemble <hi>Jezebel,</hi> then the Saints of old: And know you not that their Children you are whoſe works you do? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>any young men, their fathers <hi>were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>overs</hi> of God and <hi>Worſhippers of him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ept the Sabboth, prayed in their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies,</hi> were <hi>chaſt in their minds and body, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſt in their dealings, careful of giving offence, meek, humble, lovers of them that were good.</hi> But look upon their Children, do theſe things live and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive in them? are they the inheritours of their Fathers vertues, do they walk in the ſteps of their Godly Anceſtours? O no, it may be ſaid of them as in <hi>Judges</hi>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:134628:40"/> 2.17. You <hi>have turned quickly out o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the way wherein your fathers walked obeying the Commandment of the Lord</hi> but <hi>you do not ſo.</hi> Is not Gods ſervic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> contemned by you? Do not you loo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> upon it as a diſgrace to be Religious<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> When do you hear Gods word, or whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> doth God hear from you in prayer? An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not all dayes alike with you? even tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> holy time God hath choſen for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, is it not many times more vainly and wickedly ſpent, then the week day? What are your Conſciences but graves, wherein you have buried all the good principles you had in your education? Are not your bodies the ſinks of luſt and the epitome of Diſeaſes? You<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſtates ſo waſted in the ſervice of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Devil, that they are become but a mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> skeleton? Your breath is become mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> infectious then the ſteam of a Sepul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cher; who more bitter againſt Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs then you? Who more ready to ſhake hands with the wicked then you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Who more aſhamed of their Godly An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtours
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:134628:40"/> then you are? Do not many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f you think their ſtrictneſs and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pect walking a crime, and for fear leaſt you ſhould be involved in it, you think <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat you have no way to clear your ſelves but by doing the quite contrary? And now Sirs, do you think to ſcape? I tell you in the name of God, except you repent, your condition will be doubly miſerable.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In this life, the judgements of God will overtake you, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.20. <hi>They <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Children in whom is no faith:</hi> ſaith God in the 23, <hi>I will heap miſchief <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>em, I will ſpend mine arrows upon them.</hi> What a fatal deluge befel thoſe Sons of God, and of the Church, that corrupted themſelves, and fell from God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 7.8. What a dreadful curſe befel degenerate <hi>Cham</hi> in <hi>Noahs</hi> fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? How heavy was Gods hand upon <hi>Iſhmael</hi> and <hi>Eſau?</hi> the time would fail to let off the ſad ends wicked children of Godly Parents have come to; to ſpeak of <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu, Hophni</hi> and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:134628:41"/> 
                  <hi>Phineas, Abſolom,</hi> the Sons of good <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel,</hi> of <hi>Jehoram,</hi> the Son of good <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaphat,</hi> of the <hi>Children of Joſiah,</hi> of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>poſterity of the ſeven Aſian</hi> Churches. O you degenerate ones read theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, and tremble at them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But moſt miſerable will you be i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the day of judgement, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.13. <hi>Whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Children of the Kingdom ſhall be caſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> into utter darkneſs.</hi> There ſhall be weeping and wailing and gnaſhing of teeth; that day will be a ſad day to two ſorts of perſons, to wicked Parents and Rebellious Children; when Chriſt ſhall ſay to a Child, who taugh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou to ſwear &amp; drink? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and they ſhall ſay Lord, <hi>I had a Father and Mother did n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> more for me then beaſts do for their young I never was taught any thing was good; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> was never warned againſt ſin, I knew lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of thee and Christ,</hi> (except it were how to abuſe and prophane thy Name.) <hi>O the miſery of thoſe Parents.</hi> But o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the other ſide, when Chriſt ſhall ſay t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> another, who taught you to take ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:134628:41"/> courſes, and do ſuch things? and the Parents ſhall ſay, Lord, this our Son, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur Daughter, <hi>were Children of Belial, we warned them night and day with tears, we were gentle to them, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted them as fathers</hi> ſhould do their their Children; <hi>we corrected them, we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rayed for them,</hi> we entreated <hi>others to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ray for them,</hi> we <hi>wept over them;</hi> Lord thou knoweſt <hi>the ſighs and tears,</hi> the <hi>heart-breakings</hi> we had from them, but they would not hear: <hi>O the miſery of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat Child, and of all ſuch Children.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Now let me add but a little Counſel to you, which if followed will do you much good.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Engage your hearts to God, give up your ſelves to him.</hi> Avouch the Lord to be your God, and reſolve to be his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; then you will eaſily anſwer thoſe many temptations, that will come a ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oring for your hearts, and be very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate with you. Satan is Gods ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:134628:42"/> in ſuing for the heart, the world and the fleſh are his <hi>Pandors.</hi> Now O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> young man engage thy heart to God, and then thou mayeſt ſay, <hi>I am not mine own, I have beſtowed my affections al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, and I like my choice too well to change.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Do not think your ſelves too wiſe to learn, and too good to be taught,</hi> which is the ſin of moſt young people. It is your great wiſdome to hearken to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, <hi>Prov.</hi> 12.15. He that heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to counſel is wiſe, <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.1. A wiſe Son hears his Fathers inſtruction. <hi>There is no greater folly in young people, ahen to think themſelves wiſe enough al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready.</hi> It is reckoned in Sacred Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, great impiety not to hear inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and there is a curſe promiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe that like the deaf Adde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſtop their ears, and will not hearken to Parents, Miniſters, Godly, wiſe friends. Whom do you deſpiſe but God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf? <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3.7. You find it the brand of Reprobates, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.25. <hi>Eli hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="65" facs="tcp:134628:42"/> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ons</hi> hearkned not to the voice of their father, becauſe the Lord would ſlay them, 2 <hi>Ch.</hi> 25.16. The Prophet tells <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aziah,</hi> that his not hearkning to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, was an argument God had deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to deſtroy him. I have read a ſtory of <hi>Bernard,</hi> who had a younger brother that was a Souldier, and led a wicked life; his brother uſed many wayes to reclaim him, but he ſlighted all; Well ſaith he to him, Brother, the time may come that God <hi>may let my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ords into your heart by a hole in the ſide;</hi> not long after this gallant was wounded in his ſide: then his Brothers words came to his mind with great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhment. You that have <hi>faithfull Parents, Maſters, Friends,</hi> that advice and counſel you, <hi>take heed of ſhutting it out of your ears and hearts, leaſt God let it in with a witneſs afterwards.</hi> I would intreat young perſons to ſtudy that place, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.1, 2. It is the firſt Commandment that hath a promiſe with it, and there is a four-fold cord to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:134628:43"/> bind to the performance of it.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. It is juſt and equal, this is right:</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That it is the firſt Command, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> which leads to all the reſt; he or ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that keeps this, will keep the other; h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> or ſhe that breaks this, is in danger o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> breaking all the other, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It is a Command, with a promiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to allure them to it, and that of a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral bleſſing, and that bleſſing whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> every one deſires, long life.</p>
                  <p>And 4. The Apoſtle in <hi>Col.</hi> 3.20 adds one more; this is well-pleaſing t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Lord; and who is there that woul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not pleaſe him? O remember how i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> all other things you are willing to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> inſtructed: What Schollar is not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to learn of his teacher the Tongue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and Arts? What Servant is not willing to learn his trade, and to be inſtructed and bind himſelf ſeven, eight, nine years to learn an Art or Myſtery that he may live by hereafter? And are you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſouls nothing to you? Are you ſo wiſe for ſaving them you need no help?</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:134628:43"/>3. <hi>Though you are in ſtrength and health, likely to live many years, yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member all you Young ones that you muſt dye, and come to judgement.</hi> It is <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> counſel, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11.9. There are in <hi>Goigotha</hi> skulls of all ſizes; there is only this difference between a youth and an old man, <hi>That the one muſt dye through the neceſſity of nature, the other may die through the violence of a diſeaſe.</hi> There is nothing ſo powerful to hold men off from ſin as the meditation of death. There are ſaith one, two ſorts of trees God quickly cuts down, <hi>old trees that bear no fruit, and young trees that bear evil fruit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. Labour to work on thy heart the <hi>Meditation, how little the world bids for thy ſoul,</hi> and what inconſiderable things, thoſe vanities and pleaſures are young perſons are ſo much taken with: Many are but the <hi>pleaſures of fancy,</hi> at the beſt they are <hi>but the pleaſure of ſenſe.</hi> It is very little that young perſons know and underſtand of this, and that
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:134628:44"/> makes them ſo mad after them, and ſo deſirous to taſte and try them. We pleaſe Children with bables; and they are no better the world puts you off with, ſuch things as dare not endure a ſcrutiny at the bar of Reaſon. What do theſe things contribute to the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering your beings, and ſatisfying your appetites? I mean to the giving you true content. Alas! they are things that periſh in the uſing, and it will not be long e're you your ſelves will be of another mind. Now the more you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand youthful vanities, the more carefull you will be to paſs that age with as much innocence as may be, and to avoid thoſe ſins you muſt commit before you can come at them; and you will be afraid to venture much in the cracking that ſhell, that will yield you nothing but matter for repentance.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>Take heed you be not aſhamed of your Dutie.</hi> Satan doth many times abuſe <hi>that natural modeſtie</hi> that is in your Age, to ſtave you off from Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:134628:44"/> telling you, you will be but laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at, and ſcorned for your pains: But <hi>learn to be aſhamed of nothing but ſin;</hi> and this is that modeſty that is alwayes the companion of comlineſs and beauty, to be aſhamed to do evil: But when a man hath done evil not to be aſhamed, this is that which hath the greateſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity in it: <hi>He that is aſhamed of doing good, it is to be feared will grow past <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hame in doing evil.</hi> It is the common excuſe, I ſhall be laught at, and I am aſhamed. But if you be derided for your piety and ſingularity in Godlineſs, becauſe you will not run with the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the ſame exceſs of ryot; ſo were <hi>your betters, both Prophets and Apoſtles,</hi> nay, <hi>the Lord of both, Jeſus Christ</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was deſpiſed and mocked. But who are they that deride you? none but wicked men. And will it not be more grievous to have God laugh at your calamity, then for men to deride your piety? Choſe whether you will be aſhamed of Chriſt and his words in an
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:134628:45"/> evil Adulterous Generation, that you may avoid the reproach of the ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; or whether you will own Chriſt now, that he may own you when he comes in the Glory of his Father bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all his Holy Angels with him.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. <hi>Look well to your companie;</hi> let your delight be in the Saints that are on the earth, and in them that excell in vertue. Young trees ſeldome grow ſtraight in hedge-rows, nor young per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons good in evil company. Where your own corruption would draw you one mile, your company will draw you two<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> as a mans company is ſo is he, <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.20. <hi>Ch.</hi> 28.7.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>14.</hi> §. The Character of a wiſe Chriſhian.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>He takes the word along with him in all his concernments</hi> and actions; he that ſteers his courſe by any other rule is like a man that leaves the <hi>Pole-ſtar,</hi> and ſails by a <hi>Meteor,</hi> Read Pſal. 119.98, 99, 100.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:134628:45"/>2. <hi>He doth above all things labour to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>leaſe God.</hi> All wiſdome without this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> naught and rotten: but to make the pleaſing God our firſt and chief car eis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he trueſt wiſdom.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>He is careful to ſecure the main.</hi> The Serpents wiſdome is to ſave his head. And a Chriſtians wiſdome is to ſave his ſoul.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>He doth all things with a plain, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſt, ſincere, upright heart:</hi> he main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ains the Doves innocency with the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ents policy, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.16. True wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is a pure, chaſt, Virgin wiſdom, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat will not mix and blend with world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y and carnal policy; he knows that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty is the beſt policy, and hath the advantage of all things, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>He exerciſes a holy Government <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ver his paſſions:</hi> for there is nothing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>peaks a man further from wiſdome, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen inordinate affections. Wiſdome is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ballaſt of the mind, that keeps it ſteady. If all Government be the reſult of wiſdom, much more muſt the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:134628:46"/> of a mans ſelf ſpeak him in poſſeſſion of true wiſdom.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>His eyes are in his head;</hi> He care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully diſcerns between good and evil, between things and things, between man and man, that he may approve what is good, and reject what is evil, for otherwiſe the knowledge of good and evil is not true wiſdom.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He is careful to aptly fit means to the end.</hi> The folly of men in the falſe Church, is, they ſet up other means then God hath appointed; and the folly of men in the true Church is they ſeperate the end, and the means, and think they may come to <hi>holineſs</hi> without <hi>happineſs:</hi> But a wiſe Chriſtian knows, as there is no coming to the end but by the means, ſo no means which bring us to the end, but ſuch as are of Gods appointing.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>He is careful to time all his actions;</hi> and in order to it, to obſerve and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove all opportunities, becauſe to all things there is a time and ſeaſon that renders them beautifull and facile,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:134628:46"/> which if ſlipt, things become doubly difficult, and ſometimes impoſſible. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on if it be ſtruck while it is hot, you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay work it to any figure; ſo it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n matters of Religion. There are gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den moments, that a wiſe Chriſtian will obſerve and redeem.</p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>He doth conſider with himſelf what will be the iſſue and event of things.</hi> A wiſe man underſtands conſequences. True wiſdom, <hi>Janus like,</hi> looks back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and forward, it hath eyes before and behind. Every wiſe man holds in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence with time paſt by memory, with time preſent by prudent circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection, with time to come, by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, labouring to fore-ſee what ſuch and ſuch things will end in. Thus God himſelf to keep our firſt Parents in integrity, gave them the commination, <hi>In the day thou eateſt thereof thou ſhalt dye,</hi> expecting that in wiſdome they ſhould diſcern what the event and iſſue of diſobedience would be.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:134628:47"/>10. <hi>He doth provide for his latter end.</hi> This is a great point of wiſdome, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.29. One of the greateſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections a man attains unto is wiſdome. The proper act of wiſdome is conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; the chiefeſt point of conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is our latter end; every man muſt dye, and it is not an eaſie thing to dye well; and therefore it is wiſdom to dye daily in meditation and preparation, that when that time comes, we may have nothing to do but to dye.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="part">
               <head>§. <hi>15.</hi> Why are thoſe that have received Grace ſo troubled with diſtractions in holy duties.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Becauſe there is corruption in the beſt, which clogs and ſhackies us in our beſt duties.</hi> Remainders of ſin, will be hinderers of our cloſe communion with God; theſe dogs will be barking though their teeth be pulled out.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Becauſe Satan ſtands at our right
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:134628:47"/> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>and to withſtand us when we appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>re God,</hi> and to diſturb us in our wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ipping of him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>To ſhew unto us our need of Jeſus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hriſt,</hi> to be our High Prieſt to bear the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>niquity of our holy things.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>To teach us that when we do ſeem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> be moſt dutiful,</hi> yet even then we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave need to be <hi>moſt humble.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>To be a touchſtone of our ſpirituali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> and growth in Grace. The more ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ituality we arrive at, the fewer diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tions in Gods ſervice we ſhall meet with.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>To teach us to watch as well as pray,</hi> to keep our hearts with all diligence. Every Chriſtian in duty muſt fight as well as work.</p>
               <p n="7">7. To teach us not <hi>to make our ſelves the fountain of aſſiſtance</hi> and ſtrength in holy duties.</p>
               <p n="8">8. To make us <hi>ſtrive to be more fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent in ſpirit</hi> in ſerving the Lord. When the flame ariſes the ſmoak de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes.</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:134628:48"/>
               <p n="9">9. To ſtir <hi>us up to delight in Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vice.</hi> Our hearts will abide there wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they do delight.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>To make us long after heaven</hi> that bleſſed ſtate, where no diſtraction are.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The remedies againſt them are of tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſorts, <hi>by way of</hi> prevention, <hi>by way</hi> of care.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>By way of prevention;</hi> remembe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> theſe three things.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Holy retirement,</hi> ſometimes of body, alwayes of mind. <hi>Eſau</hi> went in the field to meditate. Enter into thy Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, ſaith our Saviour. But in public<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> there muſt be a retirement of ſpirit; cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> off thy heart from the world, and from external objects. It was a ſaying of <hi>Bernard,</hi> it is <hi>not unuſual for men of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamed fancies to be ſurrounded with mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes when alone; nor is it impoſſible for a man of a ſound ſpirit to be alone among multitudes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="77" facs="tcp:134628:48"/>2. Come to holy duties <hi>armed with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ly reſolution;</hi> ſay with <hi>David, Pſ.</hi> 71.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6. I will go in the ſtrength of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rd: Reſolve not to be taken off.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Supplication.</hi> There muſt come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ower from above, and prayer fetches in: And in prayer againſt diſtractions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>earneſt with God, for</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>The ſanctification of thy fancy</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>agination. That grace that ſanctifies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r minds, confines them; grace ſets <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r hearts upon the right object, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kes them move orderly and regular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Beg a <hi>fixed heart, Pſal.</hi> 86.11. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>avid</hi> prays, unite my heart, make it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, and he often ſpeaks of this; my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>art is fixed, or prepared.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>The ſpirit of love.</hi> The ſoul lives <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>here it loves, and cauſes an immora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on on the object; the more love to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>od, the fewer diſtractions, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ore compoſedneſs of mind.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>The grace of holy fear.</hi> In thy fear <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ill I worſhip, ſaith <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 5. Pray
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:134628:49"/> to God to poſſeſs thy ſoul with an aw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of his Glorious Majeſty.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>Beg holy Zeal.</hi> Let thy heart b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſeething hot. Flies uſe not to come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the boiling pot. Zealous Chriſtian complain leaſt of diſtractions.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>By way of Cure.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Get indignation at the firſt riſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> them.</hi> If they be <hi>injected</hi> by Satan, thro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> out the fire-ball; if thy heart ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> been <hi>the mother</hi> to conceive and brin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> them forth, let it not be <hi>the nurſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> bring them up.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Be humbled for them.</hi> Gracio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſouls cannot but be grieved at then but vain thoughts never trouble va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> men; but walk humbly with God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the ſenſe how little thy heart is wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> him.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Exerciſe faith in Chriſt for t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> pardon of them, and power againſt them</hi> when thou art troubled with theſe fie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Serpents, look to the brazen Serpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="part">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:134628:49"/>
               <head>§. <hi>16.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> brief conſideration of that common di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs of conſcience ariſing from fear that a man hath ſinned the ſin against the Holy Ghoſt, in three queſtions.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Shewing what are the reaſons why God ſuffers ſome to be exerciſed with this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>emptation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Who are they that are far from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mmitting this ſin?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>What are thoſe Graces that are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſervatives against this ſin?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Q. <hi>What are the reaſons that God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ffers ſome to be troubled with this ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is a thing of common obſervation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mong thoſe to whom diſtreſſed ſouls <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o open their maladies, that they find <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>any ſore preſſed with this tentation; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he reaſons with ſubmiſſion to better <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udgements may be ſuch as theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It many times ariſeth from ignorance, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ant of right and ſound information of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:134628:50"/> the nature and ingredients of this ſin Many poor Chriſtians charge them ſelves with it, before they underſtand what it is.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe they have not made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> right application of the word to thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> own hearts, but have been cenſoriou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and uncharitable to others, and no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they are forced by a Divine hand, whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther they will or no, to make applica<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion to themſelves; and this is God carroſive to eat out uncharitableneſs.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It may be they have been ſecu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and formal in Religion, and neglecte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the duties of it againſt the conviction o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Word and Conſcience, and abate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in their affections to God, to the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nances, to the Children of God. Sin againſt light and back-ſliding, thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in ſuch and ſuch a degree they do no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conſtitute this ſin, yet they look too lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It is to make others fear, and tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more heed to their wayes. When we ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God as it were letting our brothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:134628:50"/> upon the rack; this is to check our negligence, to be a bridle to our looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It is to exerciſe the gifts and graces of others, both Miniſters and Chriſtians, to put them upon the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of prayer, conſolation, pitty, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, labour, brotherly kindneſs, and the like.</p>
               <p n="6">6. They may be exerciſed with it to fit them for ſome eminent ſervice and imployment, as to make ſome open confeſſion of the Faith, or to make them experimental comforters of others, with the comforts wherewith they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have been comforted of God, or to prepare them for undergoing ſome heavy outward affliction, which ſeems <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight to thoſe that have had a wounded ſpirit, or to make them live a more ſtrict and exemplary life, or to poſſeſs ſome greater meaſure of ſpiritual joy, or to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ortifie them againſt the aſſaults of ſome beloved ſin, or to undergo ſome fierce conflict with Satan; ſome or all theſe
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:134628:51"/> may be the condition of the party here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after; and God is now fitting and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring them by this trouble for it.</p>
               <p>They may think they have commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this ſin by Gods leaving them to hearken to Satans perſwaſion. They fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in believing God who ſpoke for their good, and now they believe Satan who ſpeaks for their ruine; they did not hearken to the motions of Gods ſpirit for their conſolation, and now they hearken to the falſe reaſonings of an unbelieving heart prompted by Satan for their vexation. Satan was not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly more diligent to draw them on to ſin, then he is now to keep them from comfort; and their own perverſneſs did not then make them further from inſtruction, then now it doth from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2. Queſt.</hi> Who are they that are far from committing this ſin?</p>
               <p>The ſolution of this may ſerve as a remedy againſt this diſtreſs; for who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:134628:51"/> finds in himſelf theſe things, may be confident he is not guilty of this ſin.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They are far from committing this ſin, that do eſteem Chriſt, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to enjoy him, and are willing to be ſubject to his Authority.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They that do truly deſire to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour Chriſt, not only inwardly in their hearts, but outwardly in their lives and converſations by words and actions.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They whoſe illumination is attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with reformation, who not onely know the Truth, but love and obey it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Thoſe who with well to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Goſpel, and people of Chriſt, that for <hi>Sions</hi> ſake cannot hold their peace.</p>
               <p n="5">5. They who cleave to the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, though they want comfort, that wait upon the Lord who hides himſelf from the houſe of <hi>Jacob.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. They who deſire the efficacy of the miniſtry on the ſouls of others, who
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:134628:52"/> can rejoyce when ſouls are converted, and are glad to ſee that Grace in others they want, and that grieve when the edification of ſouls is oppoſed and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed.</p>
               <p n="7">7. They that aſpire after a holy life, that are ſtudents for piety, and mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for iniquity. Theſe have not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3. Qu.</hi> What are thoſe Graces that are preſervatives againſt this ſin?</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>A chearfulneſs in the ſervice and wayes of Christ.</hi> Serve the Lord with gladneſs, account not his Commands grievous.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A ſincere love to Father, Son and Spirit. This ſin is committed out of malice and hatred.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A daily deſiring, thirſting after Chriſt, ever deſiring Chriſt will keep us from ever deſpiſing him.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A labouring to get heat unto our light, that our knowledge may be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with a change in heart and life.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:134628:52"/>5. A daily care to perſevere, and hold on in Religion and Grace, with a jealouſie of our ſelves leaſt we ſhould be guilty of declining and back ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
               <p n="6">6. A pleading and ſtanding up for the truth in our places and callings with courage and wiſdom.</p>
               <p n="7">7. A perfecting holineſs in the fear of the Lord, avoiding not only all groſs ſins, but alſo, as much as we can, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſelves from infirmities, at leaſt not allowing our ſelves in them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="part">
               <head>§. <hi>17.</hi> The ſpirituals mans aime, or a reſolution of an important and ſerious queſtion, concerning our aimes and intentions, whether they be for God or the world.</head>
               <p>Aims and intentions are ſecret things, removed from the cognizance of others. The rectitude of intention contributes ſo much to the acceptation of our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices with God, that without this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:134628:53"/> though never ſo materially good and plauſible can denominate us ſincere in his ſight; or prevail for any acceptance with him: Now though o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are not competent judges of our ends, yet if we will deal faithfully and truly with our own ſouls, we may know them by ſuch plain things as theſe are:</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>By our deſires.</hi> Try thy heart by this, whether thou doſt deſire moſt to be with God, or to be in the world. That which is our end we would be in the fulleſt enjoyment of.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>By thy hopes.</hi> What is it thou ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt for? is it to grow great or rich in the world? or is it that thou art approv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of God, and in favour with him? That which is thy chiefeſt hope is thy end.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>By thy delights.</hi> Doſt thou ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the world, that if that flow in, and that thou haſt any probable aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of its continuance, thou findeſt thou canſt be contented without God?
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:134628:53"/> or doſt thou account thy ſelf miſerable whatſoever thou enjoyeſt, except thou have ſome ſoul communion with God, and canſt find ſome taſts of his love, even in outward mercies, and thoſe taſts car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying thy ſoul to delight more and more in God as the fountain of them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Examine how thy heart is <hi>affected upon the loſs of outward things:</hi> What is it grieves thee moſt, the burning thy houſe, loſs of trade, death of friends, or the want of Gods preſence, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhonour of his name, the danger of lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Goſpel, and the like? that which is our end, we are grieved for, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſappointed of.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>If the world be thy darling, thou wilt be affraid to own Religion</hi> when it expoſes thee to danger, ſhame and loſs: alwayes worldlings are for an eaſie, cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditable, che<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p Religion: But if God have thy heart, thou art jealous leaſt the world ſhould draw thee from God, and thou wilt account no pains too much for him, thou wilt be diligent in
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:134628:54"/> the uſe of all means. In the ſervice of God thou wilt account loſſes gain, and think thy ſelf abundantly honoured in being accounted worthy to be diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured for Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That <hi>which is a man's end he will plead for.</hi> We ſee prophane men plead for the world; <hi>groſs ſins</hi> are with them <hi>ſmall ſins,</hi> nay, <hi>no ſins,</hi> nay ſometimes <hi>commendable things,</hi> or at leaſt <hi>indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent;</hi> for ends will make men find cut many Topicks to argue from. Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous apparel is but decency, drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is but good fellowſhip; they can ſay much for unlawful gaming, wanton dalliances, ſtage-playes, recreations on the Lords day; Alas, ſay they, theſe are but innocent Divertiſements for the body and mind: But thoſe that make God their end will plead for him, they ſtand up for his Name, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is Word, his People, <hi>Wiſdom is juſtified of her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren;</hi> they have much to ſay for <hi>devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> for <hi>mortification,</hi> for <hi>faſting</hi> and <hi>praying,</hi> for <hi>holy conference,</hi> for <hi>modeſt
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:134628:54"/> apparel,</hi> for <hi>ſobriety and temperance,</hi> for circumſpect walking, and the like.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>He that ſerves the world will ſuffer much for it,</hi> in <hi>his body</hi> by pinching it, in <hi>his name</hi> and <hi>reputation</hi> by reproach, (for even a covetous miſer ſhall have ſome ſcoffs; he will make ſuch pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful complaints, and ſuch ridiculous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes, and do ſuch baſe drudgery, the world will laugh at him) yet he ſuffers all this becauſe it is his end: So he that ſerves God is willing to ſuffer for God, to part with all for him when he calls for it, to endure ſcoffs and jeers for his not complying with the Vices of the world.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, if God and the World call, whom doſt thou follow? the Bell touls, the Play-bill is ſet up, whither doſt thou go? Here's the Bible or a good Book, there is the Tavern, or the Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming houſe; God calls to the one, the World to the other, whom doſt thou obey? If a Lacquey follows two Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, when they part, he whom he
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:134628:55"/> follows we know is his Maſter; that which a man follows from morning to night, from week to week, and leave other things to follow, that is his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, that he ſerves, and that is his end.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="part">
               <head>§. <hi>18.</hi> How muſt we carry our ſelves to God a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our friend.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Truſt him</hi> becauſe he is faithful.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prize him,</hi> becauſe he is ſo tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently excellent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Be adviſed by him,</hi> for he is infinitely wiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Suffer for him,</hi> for Chriſt did ſo fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Delight in him,</hi> becauſe he is ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Be zealous for his Glory,</hi> and grieved at his diſhonour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Love his Children</hi> for his ſake.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Long to hear from him,</hi> and let him hear often from us.</p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:134628:55"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rejoyce in his gifts,</hi> but more in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reſence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Invite him to come unto us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Do nothing to grieve him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Be comforted in this, our friend will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ever be our enemy, and our enemy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hall never find us friendleſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="part">
               <head>§. <hi>19.</hi> Of the Providence of God in two caſes, how it is abuſed, and how it may be improved.</head>
               <p>The Doctrine of Gods providence is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> moſt comfortable Doctrine to Gods Children, and that which we ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>abour to have a diſtinct knowledge of. Two things at preſent I ſhall briefly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouch upon.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>To ſhew how the providence of God is abuſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>How the providence of God may be improved for the comfort of the Godly, in ſome common caſes that may befall them.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:134628:56"/>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>1. Queſt. <hi>How is the providence o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> God is abuſed?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I anſwer, the providence of God i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> moſt ſadly abuſed theſe four wayes:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>When the providence of God is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> obſerved and taken notice of,</hi> hereupon God loſes that Glory he might have from us, and we loſe that comfort we might have, if we did obſerve how al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> things come from God, and are ordered by him. It is true, that there are my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious workings in the providence of God, which ſome think was ſet out by the hands under the wings of the living creatures, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 1.8.</p>
                  <p>But of thoſe things that are ſeen and viſible, we take little notice of them, of which God complains, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.12. There are ſeveral things in the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, the not obſerving where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſpeaks us guilty of abuſing it.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. When we take no notice how the attributes of God, his wiſdom, holineſs, power, truth, love, juſtice, ſhine forth in all his works.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:134628:56"/>2. When we obſerve not <hi>the buſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>urning and not conſuming,</hi> the eminent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reſervation God gives to his Church, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ending them full and ſeaſonable relief <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n all troubles and dangers; the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence of the Church, when the deſign, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ower and malice of the world is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ainſt it, ſeems no leſs then a continued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iracle, to one that weighs all circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ances.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. When we obſerve not how emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ently God infatuates enemies, diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oints and fruſtrates their expectations, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d that when they have travelled, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ought things to the birth, that all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ings are ready for execution, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>gn and counſels are ripe for action, then God overthrows all; theſe are things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat run into our ſenſes daily, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y age gives proof of them, yet who ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rves theſe things?</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Not obſerving Gods vindicative <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſtice in a way of retaliation, when God doth, as we may ſay, cry quit with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>icked men, puniſhing them in that
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:134628:57"/> very way and kind they have ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, as in <hi>Adonibezek,</hi> Judges <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>in the caſe of Sodom,</hi> burning with luſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it is burnt with fire; they were guilty of unnatural luſt, and fire hath an unna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tural motion, it comes downward. Thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> God threatens <hi>drunkards, Hab.</hi> 2.15<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 16. to give them cup for cup, ſpewin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for ſpewing. So <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.1. a Text ofte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to be read to oppreſſours and perfidiou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> men: You ſhall have ſpoiling for ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and treachery for treachery. Agai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Joel</hi> 3.6, 7, 8. a good Text for cru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> men, God threatens to pay them in thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> own kind: Therefore <hi>David</hi> ofte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> magnifies the Lord for this work of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> providence, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7.16. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.15, 16 And at the deſtruction of <hi>Babylon, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Angel of the waters</hi> glorifies God fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> this, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.5. becauſe he had <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> judged;</hi> thus they ſinned, thus the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> were puniſhed.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. When we obſerve not how th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> providence of God is a fulfilling th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Word of God. The providence of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:134628:57"/> well underſtood and applyed, is a moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lear excellent comment upon Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ord. Thus we ſee <hi>Jehu,</hi> a naughty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an, yet 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 9.26, 37. in the caſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f Gods juſtice upon wicked <hi>Ahabs</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>mily; mark how he comments, <hi>This is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he word of the Lord, this is the fulfilling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uch a threatning:</hi> The thing in it ſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as good, to obſerve how God in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orks makes good his word; but the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ffection in <hi>Jehu</hi> was naught. We have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> example of Chriſts Diſciples when he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is purging the Temple, <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is Diſciples remembred it was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n, <hi>The zeal of thy houſe hath eaten me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>p.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Some ſay, if two Lutes be equally <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ung and tuned, though they be laid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſeveral places, yet ſtrike one, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ther will ſound; ſo when God ſtrikes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pon the ſtring of providence, preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the word anſwers it; this is done, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>at the Scripture might be fulfilled: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he bread I eat is a fulfilling the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ture, he is ever mindful of his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:134628:58"/> he hath given meat to them tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>fear him, Pſal.</hi> 111.5. The preſervation I have are a fulfilling the <hi>word, Pſal.</hi> 91. he ſhall keep thee in all thy wayes. A ſeaſonable calling to mind the word o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> God when we ſee the works of God, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a ſign of a gracious heart, and a ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied memory; whereas the not regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, the not ſeeing him in the things he doth and gives to us, is a ſign of a degenerate heart, and the abuſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Gods providence.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Providence is abuſed, when from thence men take occaſion to ſin from it</hi> and that among others is done theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> three wayes;</p>
                  <p n="1">1. When any conclude they may ſin becauſe God in his providence can tur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it to good. This is that preſumptio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> corrected by the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.8. Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> us do evil that good may come of it which was a ſlander caſt on the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, as if they had taught ſuch Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. God is indeed the ſoveraig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cauſe of all events, yet this excuſes no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:134628:58"/> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments; for what God doth very juſtly, men may do very wickedly.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. When we do not diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween tempting providences, and the commands of God: we muſt follow pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence no further then we have the Word for our rule: Becauſe <hi>Achan</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed providence, he ſtole the <hi>Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> garment; but becauſe <hi>David</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the word of God, he durſt do no harm to <hi>Saul,</hi> though providence had put him in his hand. There are tempting and permitting as well as dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting and commanding providences; and it requires a great deal of wiſdome to cut an even thread, between Gods providence and mans improvidence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween providences of wrath, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences of mercy. We err moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly when we do engage in actions providence ſeems to favour, when there is a plain expreſs word againſt them; when we miſ-interpret Gods provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, to think God in his works likes that, and encourages to that, he hath in
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:134628:59"/> his word forbidden, is as ſad a miſtake as a poor creature can run into, and it is a great ſign of infatuation; when a man ſees and obſerves what may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage him, and thinks himſelf clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and powerful called to it, and is ſtark blind, and can take no notice of the ſtops, checks, rebukes, and diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements God lays in his way. To make providence a cloak for any unlawful action, is to abuſe the dealings of God. Remember, God is not mocked, nor can any fig-leaves hide from him, who hath a penetrating eye, and whoſe judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is according to truth.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. When the providences of God in his mercies and bleſſings are perverted and turned out of their right channel, and made to ſerve pride, luſt, envy, lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ury, and the like; and this way the providence of God is moſt univerſally abuſed in the world, both by Heathens and Chriſtians.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>We abuſe the providence of God, when we make an evil conſtruction of the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:134628:59"/> afflictions of Gods people;</hi> when we conclude from thence they are wicked men, hypocrites, that God hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken them, and caſt them off. Thus <hi>Jobs</hi> friends dealt with him, and the wicked with <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 71.10, 11. and the <hi>Jews with Chriſt:</hi> Whereas all theſe providences are either probative, corrective, or purgative: Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, they are none of Gods people, becauſe they are afflicted, is a horrible abuſe of Gods providence, a condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the generation of the juſt, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues deſperate ignorance, or ſomething worſe.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>When we inſult over thoſe that are in miſery,</hi> a thing too common among thoſe that are called Chriſtians. There is a ſpirit in the world that rejoyces in others afflictions, a generation that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lap their hands at our diviſions, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſſes, or ſufferings, and ſay as they in the Pſalms, <hi>ſo would we have it:</hi> But as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.5. <hi>He that is glad at calamities ſhall not go unpuniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi>
                     <pb n="100" facs="tcp:134628:60"/> If any ſhould rejoyce in the diſmal burning of <hi>London,</hi> and ſay it was well burnt, but in an ill time, God himſelf hath ſaid of ſuch, <hi>they ſhall not go un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed;</hi> the Devil himſelf ſhall as ſoon eſcape the vengeance of eternal fire, as ſuch ſhall eſcape the judgements of God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>2. Queſt. <hi>How providence is to be improved for the comfort of the Godly, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanced in ſome common caſes, may and do befall them.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="case">
                     <head>1. Caſe<hi> is, Concerning the deadneſs and inefficacy of means.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>I call that deadneſs of means, when there is either a total inaptitude in the means, or no ſuitableneſs or congruity in the means to the end, as in <hi>Abrahams Caſe, Rom.</hi> 4. There was no likelihood that ſuch an ancient couple as <hi>Abraham and Sarah</hi> ſhould have a young child: So in the deſtruction of <hi>Jericho,</hi> that the compaſſing the City in a kind of
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:134628:60"/> proceſſion, ſix dayes ſhould contribute to the taking of the City: What effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ſeemed in this? So, that <hi>Cyrus</hi> a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then ſhould proclaim liberty to the <hi>Jews</hi> to return to their own Land, and that he ſhould contribute to the building the Temple to the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> was a very unlikely thing, no one would have thought him a fit perſon for ſuch a work, that he ſhould become another <hi>Solomon</hi> in this particular.</p>
                     <p>Thus many times a Chriſtian ſees no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ively ſuitable means to bring about that good he deſires and expects. In this Caſe we may be comforted;</p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>Becauſe the fountain from whence we expect all good to flow is God:</hi> Now God is not tyed to means; all means work only by way of inſtrument. If a man be ſick, phyſick is the ordinary way to cure him, but the fountain of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ife and health is God; and therefore God many times bleſſes poor, weak, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ikely means, to reſtore a man to health: So when a man is poor, friends and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:134628:61"/> are the ordinary way to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him; but ſometimes God makes ſtrangers and enemies to do it: whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the inſtrument, it is God that ſends the ſupply, <hi>Phil</hi> 4.19.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. God many times denies and hides ſuitable and lively means, becauſe <hi>we ſhould put too much truſt in them;</hi> and it is our over-prizing, and over-expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting from creatures, makes God to put a deadneſs into them.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Providence <hi>ſeldome appears in means of our chooſing,</hi> or works by tools of our appointing. When we limit the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to time, to perſons, to means, God alwayes holds back his hand, for God will not be preſcribed by us what he ſhall do.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. <hi>Divine providence can put life into the deadeſt means that are;</hi> he can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper the moſt unlikely means; he can m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ke dry bones live. This many times he doth to ſhew, that he can quicken the dead, that he is wiſe in counſel, and excellent in working.</p>
                     <pb n="103" facs="tcp:134628:61"/>
                  </div>
                  <div type="case">
                     <head>
                        <hi>2. Caſe.</hi> The croſneſs of events.</head>
                     <p>Croſs events are when things do fall out contrary to expectation; when we look for light, but behold darkneſs, for peace, but behold trouble, for healing, but lo a breach, for eaſe, and behold a burthen; when we have ſaid of ſuch a thing, ſurely <hi>it ſhall comfort us concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſorrow;</hi> and when it hath been produced, it hath been either a rod to beat us, or a Serpent to bite us: this is that cauſes great trouble and ſadneſs of heart. <hi>Deceived hopes trouble us more then preſent wants.</hi> Preſent wants may pain us, but deceived expectations ſhame us, and a rational creature en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures any thing better then ſhame, which is cauſed not only from doing things againſt common principles, but from loſing and miſſing our expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Therefore <hi>David</hi> prays, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.116. that he may not be aſhamed of his hopes. This the Godly meet with at
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:134628:62"/> every turn: Many times children, other relations, callings, do not anſwer our expectations, all things go croſs with him: <hi>In this caſe conſider.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>There are certain Royalties in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine providence, with which we may not meddle.</hi> We muſt ſubmit to God, for as God is the cauſe of all actions why they are, ſo he is the cauſe of the ceſſation of acts.</p>
                     <p>As God hath the higheſt reaſon for what he doth, ſo he hath good reaſon why he doth not do ſuch a thing, or why he doth invert or ſtop ſuch a thing.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>How croſs ſoever the events of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence are, they are alwayes founded upon unerring wiſdome, and unſpotted goodneſs.</hi> God knows well enough what he doth, he works all things according to the counſel of his own will, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.11. For as in the body of man the foot hath an eye to direct it, and in the ſoul the will of man hath the light of the underſtanding to go before it; ſo God
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:134628:62"/> would have us to conceive of him, that the light of adviſed wiſdome is with him in all he wills or works. In all our deſires therefore we muſt put them up with a reſervation of the will of God, and how croſs ſoever things fall out to our hopes, yet remember what God works is better then what we pray for; we may err in our prayers, but God never miſtakes in what he doth.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. <hi>Croſs events in providence are many times the puniſhment of ſome ſin in us;</hi> either it is for our untimely deſire of things, or our inordinate deſire, or the neglect of ſome duty required as preparatory to make ſuch a thing come as a bleſſing.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. <hi>Croſs events many times come from Divine Love.</hi> A Father will not let the Child have a knife, or climb up in ſome high place, becauſe he knows he will hurt himſelf: So God many times ſees if he ſhould gratifie and ſucceed our hopes and our deſires, we ſhould but thereby be rendred more uncapable of
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:134628:63"/> ſerving him, we ſhould be prone to ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate in the creature, we ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract more falls and bruiſes. Conſider then <hi>God may grant in anger, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold in love.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">5. <hi>If God in his providence do croſs us in one thing, it may be it is to beſtow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us ſome better thing.</hi> When he ſhuts the hand of his common bounty, it is that he may open the hand of his ſpecial grace.</p>
                     <p>(Laſtly) <hi>In ſuch providences God doth not ſimply croſs us, but many times by things and wayes that ſeem contrary he gives the good that we deſire.</hi> Gods way for <hi>Iſrael</hi> to <hi>Canaan</hi> was a ſtraight way, <hi>or a right way,</hi> Pſal. 107.7. Though it had many turnings and windings, going backwards and forwards; So God makes the croſſing us for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent a ripening circumſtance for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; here is all the difference, God brings the mercy round about, and we look for it ſtraight forward.</p>
                     <pb n="107" facs="tcp:134628:63"/>
                  </div>
                  <div type="case">
                     <head>
                        <hi>3. Caſe.</hi> The ſtrength and ſucceſſiveneſs of Afflictions.</head>
                     <p>That is, when afflictions come one upon the neck of another, like <hi>Jobs</hi> meſſengers, and a whole ſeries of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences are againſt; as in <hi>Jacobs caſe, Gen.</hi> 42.36. <hi>Joſeph</hi> is not, and <hi>Simeon</hi> is not, and ye will take <hi>Benjamin</hi> alſo, <hi>all theſe things are againſt me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1. Conſider, <hi>all afflictions take their commiſſion from divine providence;</hi> there is no rod but is of Gods making and ſending, <hi>Job</hi> 5.6. Affliction ſprings not out of the duſt: That wicked King or Lord, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 6.33. raiſed a true Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, when he ſaid, this evil is of the Lord: But he made an ill application, when he ſaid I will tarry no longer.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>There is a Divine providence that qualifies ſucceſſive afflictions,</hi> and makes them all mercies to good men. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever repeated rebukes, and reiterated ſtroaks are to wicked men, they prove
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:134628:64"/> good phyſick to the Godly.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. <hi>Divine providence proportions theſe renewed afflictions to our diſeaſe;</hi> If he ſends many afflictions, it is, becauſe <hi>we need them,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.6. manifold temptations come not but where need is. We ſerve divers luſts; no wonder God ſends divers tryals. <hi>Job</hi> could not have been without one of his afflictions. Many times ſingle afflictions do not make us underſtand; we look upon the firſt as an accident, as a by-blow, but when it comes again and again, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to think what is the matter, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what is amiſs. When the report was brought to <hi>Galienus the Emperour, Aegypt</hi> was loſt, what then ſaith he, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not I live without the flax of <hi>Aegypt?</hi> And when it was told him <hi>Aſia</hi> was loſt; and cannot I live without the delicacies of <hi>Aſia?</hi> Such a kind of ſpirit that ſlights ſingle afflictions, makes God dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble his ſtroak. When God muſters up an Army of afflictions, and purſues us with Fire, Sword, and Peſtilence, it becomes
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:134628:64"/> us to think what is the cauſe, ſure here is ſomewhat done more then ordinary, ſure there is ſome <hi>Achan,</hi> ſome abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable thing among us: We do not ſend a train of Artillery, and an Army to kill waſps: nor doth the wiſe God make ſuch preparations for death, but where there is juſt occaſion given.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Theſe troubles, though they come thick like hail-ſtones, <hi>yet they are all meaſured and moderated by God, as to the time and continuance.</hi> There will be a laſt affliction, the laſt plague, the laſt enemy to Gods people; all afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as they are from the will of God, ſo every circumſtance, the height, breadth, length of every one is meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by God, and that is a ſingular com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="case">
                     <head>
                        <hi>4. Caſe.</hi> The blaſting of probabilities.</head>
                     <p>That is, when things have been regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly ſought of God by holy means, and in a lawful way, and we have come neer the Mercy, in ſight of it, things
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:134628:65"/> have been wound up to the top, of a ſuddee all things run backward, and we loſe the ſight of the mercy; ſo that we are to begin all anew.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Conſider, <hi>God checks viſible pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babilities, leaſt we ſhould aſcribe all to means,</hi> and rob him of his Glory.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>To ſhew us the vanity of Creatures,</hi> and to convince us of the folly of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing our ſelves ſo much comfort and ſatisfaction from them. The Creatures promiſe us great things, and we are too apt to believe them. Riches promiſe to eaſe us of our care and labour, and we many times promiſe our ſelves a writ of eaſe too; but they do but increaſe our cares; they promiſe liberty, but they bring us into bondage; they promiſe us contentment, but they fill us with diſquietings and vexation, and ſo in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things: We expect great matters from changes and alterations. The Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant promiſes himſelf great matters in his freedome, the ſingle man in his mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, the heir in getting out of ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:134628:65"/> and minority: But all theſe things are fewel to enflame our deſires, rather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hen food to ſatisfie. But there is no way to make us believe it till we feel it; therefore God blaſts many things that are probably like to prove com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, that we may experimentally ſee the vanity of Creatures.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. <hi>God many times interrupts proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, to ſee how we can behave our ſelves in the midſt of improbabilities,</hi> whether we can live upon a promiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>or no. For though a promiſe be not ſo ſenſible a ground to relie upon, yet a promiſe is a ſurer ground then the moſt probable providence that is. In that God hath promiſed to be my God, and my exceeding great reward, and hath ſaid, if I commit my way to him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he will bring it to paſs, this is a better ground to reſt and ſtay upon, then if I had all the probable means in the world. Now when God cuts off probable ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours and ſupports from us, it is that we ſhould live more upon himſelf and his promiſe.</p>
                     <pb n="112" facs="tcp:134628:66"/>
                  </div>
                  <div type="case">
                     <head>
                        <hi>5. Caſe.</hi> The pinching wants of our preſent Condition.</head>
                     <p>That is, when there is a thinneſs and ſcantineſs of outward proviſion: many mouths, little meat; many backs, little rayment; many wants, and ſmall ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes; we have nothing but what we have from hand to mouth. In this caſe,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Conſider, <hi>Divine providence is a daily care.</hi> Chriſts Diſciples muſt take no care for to morrow, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.34. The whole congregation of <hi>Iſrael</hi> muſt ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Manna day by day, Exod.</hi> 16.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> They ſhall gather a certain rate every day, that I may prove them. <hi>Vatablu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> refers Gods proving <hi>Iſrael</hi> to this par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticular Law of gathering <hi>Manna;</hi> thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> was a great tryal of their dependance o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> God, and obedience to him.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>God can ſend means ſucceſſivel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> day by day,</hi> as he did to <hi>Elijah.</hi> Is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the earth the Lords, and the fulneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> thereof? God hath ſtrange wayes t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="113" facs="tcp:134628:66"/> provide for his. In the year 1573. when <hi>Rochel</hi> was beſieged by the <hi>French</hi> Kings Army, God ſent them in daily with the Tyde an infinite number of ſmall fiſhes, ſuch as before that time were never ſeen in that Haven, and after the Siege ended retired again. God can lengthen out a little means, and put a ſecret ſweetneſs and fatneſs and bleſſing into the morſels of the Righteous.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. <hi>God ſees a depending life beſt for his Children. Aegypt</hi> was a Countrey that owed its fertility to the over-flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>River Nilus:</hi> This was not judged by God ſo fit a place for <hi>Iſrael</hi> as <hi>Canaan,</hi> a Land that was watered with rain from Heaven; they depended on God for that rain. Our wiſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſees that a dependance on his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidential care is beſt for us, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath taught us to pray, <hi>Give us this day our daily bread.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="case">
                     <head>
                        <hi>6. Caſe,</hi> Is concerning poſterity.</head>
                     <p>I ſhould, <hi>ſaith many a man,</hi> do well
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:134628:67"/> enough for my ſelf, but what if I ſhould dye, and leave many poor Children in a helpleſs condition; this troubles me more then my perſonal calamities do.</p>
                     <p>To this I propoſe but this one conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration from the providence of God.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Law ſaith, the King never dies:</hi> So I ſay, <hi>the providence of God never dies;</hi> though thou dieſt, God ſtill lives. Providence is not reſtrained to one age of a mans life, or to elderly and grown perſons: providence doth eminently concern it ſelf for little Children. What care did God take for <hi>Iſhmael</hi> when he was a little child? How ſtrangely did providence work for <hi>Moſes,</hi> when he was hid three months! and <hi>David,</hi> Pſ. 27.10. ſuppoſes that if Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould forſake him, (for the words do ſeem to be <hi>vox fidei,</hi> the language of <hi>Davids</hi> Faith.) Yet God will take care of him, and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.41. <hi>He ſetteth the Poor on High from Affliction, and makes his Families like a flock.</hi> A flock of ſheep are maintained with a little
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:134628:67"/> charge, the taking out of ſome, is often a means to preſerve the reſt; they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main a flock ſtill. God can make one Child a help to Father and Mother, and all his Brethren; ſo <hi>Joſeph</hi> was to <hi>Jacobs Family.</hi> Make it thy care thy Children may be Gods, and then leave them to his providence, with whom the <hi>Fatherleſs find mercy.</hi> The good of poſterity lies in the ſame hand of providence thy own good lies in. Do thou like <hi>Abraham</hi> command thy Children and Houſhold to keep the way of the Lord, to do Juſtice and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and God will bring upon thee and thine the <hi>bleſſing of Abraham,</hi> to be a God <hi>to thee, and to thy Seed,</hi> Gen. 18.19.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="to_the_reader">
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:134628:68"/>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THe enſuing Catechiſm is for the moſt part taken out of <hi>Mr. Hierons</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſme, and is only the latter part of it, which contains general directions for Holineſs and Righteouſneſs applyed to particulars, both to our daily carriage and to our Age, duty in our Calling and Relation; and becauſe it is out of print, I was very deſirous to have at leaſt this part reprinted, becauſe it doth ſo pithi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, plainly and orderly ſet down Relative Duties: Some Alteration and addition I have made for illuſtration and applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſake, which I hope thou wilt have no cauſe to complain of. Read, Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, Pray and practiſe, and God will give a bleſſing to thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="part">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:134628:68"/>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>§. <hi>20. 1.</hi> Directions for a mans daily carriage.</head>
                  <p>Queſtion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WHat muſt our work be in the morning?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> To let our Prayer come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, and to praiſe his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, which he ſhews in our continual pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation; and thus to do is to awake with God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 88.13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 59.16.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>What must our apparel be?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Such as becometh thoſe that profeſs the fear of God, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.10.<note n="b" place="bottom">Therefore neither coſtly beyond ability, nor garniſh beyond modeſty.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>What is next to be done?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> We muſt follow our own bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs with quietneſs,<note n="c" place="bottom">That is in thoſe particular Callings God hath ſet us in.</note> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.11. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.12.</p>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:134628:69"/>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>What muſt chiefly be cared for in our buſineſs?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> To walk with God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.22.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>What is it to walk with God in our Calling?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. To ſet the Lord alwayes before us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.8.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. To labour to approve our ſelves to him in well pleaſing, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.9.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. To acknowledge him in all our wayes, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.6.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. To refer all to his Glory, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>What muſt our Speech be?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Gracious alwayes, <hi>Col.</hi> 4.6.<note n="d" place="bottom">Such as may witneſs Grace in the heart.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>Why must we be ſo careful of our ſpeech?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe for every idle word we muſt give account, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.36, 37.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>Why elſe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:134628:69"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe if any man ſeem to be Religious, and bridles not his tongue, his Religion is vain, <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.26.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>What things must we chiefly avoid in ſpeaking?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Lying, ſwearing, filthineſs, fooliſh talking, jeſting and railing, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.25. <hi>ch.</hi> 5.4. <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.12. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11.<note n="e" place="bottom">This is called, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.29. rotten communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe it diſcovers a rotten, corrupt heart.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>What company muſt we keep?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> We muſt deſire and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to be companions of them that fear God, and let our delight be in the Saints which are on earth, and in them that excel in vertue, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.3. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.63.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>Is there any danger in evil company?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, for a companion of fools ſhall be deſtroyed, <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.20. <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.7.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>What muſt we do in ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:134628:70"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Learn not their evil wayes, and if ſinners entice thee, conſent not to them, <hi>Ier.</hi> 10.2. <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.10.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>What muſt we do when we come to our meat?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> We muſt do as Chriſt did, look up to Heaven and give thanks, <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.19.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>How many things muſt we look to in our diet chiefly, as we are Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and reaſonable Creatures?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Three things.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the firſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> That our uſe of the Creatures be with ſobriety, leaſt our hearts be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-charged with ſurfeting and drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.34.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the ſecond?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> That we forget not God, nor the operation of his hands, feeding our ſelves without fear, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.10, 11, 12. <hi>Jud. Ep.</hi> 12.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the third?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> That of that which remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:134628:70"/> nothing be loſt, <hi>John</hi> 6.12.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>Ought not ſome time to be ſet apart every day for ſpiritual uſes?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> We ought to redeeme the time, becauſe the dayes are evil, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.16.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>May not Recreation be uſed?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, there is a time to laugh, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 3.4.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>What kind of ſports may we uſe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Such as be harmleſs and of good report, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.8.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>What particular Rules are there about Recreations?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Four eſpecially.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the firſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Recreation muſt not be in the uſe of holy things, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.7.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the ſecond?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> That we make not ſport with the ſins or offences of men, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.136. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.8.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the third?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> That our rejoycing hinder not
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:134628:71"/> better duties, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.16, 17.<note n="f" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Paul</hi> joynes rejoycing with Prayer, to teach that that mirth is evil that hinders or unfits for Prayer.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the fourth?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> That we cauſe not our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian liberty to be evil ſpoken of, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.16.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is our evening duty?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> Prayer, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.17.<note n="g" place="bottom">That the ſin of the day paſt may be pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and that the night following we may be preſerved.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What elſe muſt we do?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> Examine our ſelves upon our beds, and every man to ſay to himſelf, what have I done? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.6.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>How many things make ſleep com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> Two. The firſt is honeſt labour, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.11.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the ſecond?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> A Godly care to thrive in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.13. compared with 21.24.</p>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:134628:71"/>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>How muſt ſleep be uſed?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> Love it not, leaſt thou come to poverty, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.13.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>§. <hi>2.</hi> The Magiſtrates Duty.</head>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the principal duty of the Magiſtrate?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> To beautifie the houſe of God, <hi>Ezra</hi> 7.27.<note n="a" place="bottom">To advance True Religion; and this belongs to all in Authority according to their place, even from the King to the meaneſt Officer.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>How muſt he carry himſelf among the people?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> As a Miniſter of God for their good, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>How ſhall he procure it?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> By being for the praiſe of them that do well, and for the puniſhment of evil doers, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.14.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What kind of men are fit to be Magiſtrates?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:134628:72"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:134628:72"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:134628:73"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> Men of courage, fearing God, dealing truly, and hating covetouſneſs, <hi>Exod.</hi> 81.21.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>§. <hi>3.</hi> The Subjects Duty.</head>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the Subjects duty?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> To be ſubject for conſcience-ſake, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.5.<note n="b" place="bottom">Knowing Magiſtracy to be Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What elſe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> To pray for Kings, and all that are in Authority, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What beſides?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Not to curſe the King ſo much as in a thought, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.20.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>Is there any other duty?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> We muſt not joyne our ſelves with them that are ſeditious, <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.21.<note n="c" place="bottom">Theſe three laſt duties flow from the firſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection for Conſcience-ſake; he that is ſo, will pray, will neither in heart curſe, nor in act rebell.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:134628:73"/>
                  <head>§. <hi>4.</hi> The Miniſters Duty.</head>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the Miniſters Duty?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> To take heed to his Miniſtry that he hath received, that he do fulfill it, <hi>Col.</hi> 4.17.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>How may that be done?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> Several wayes.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the firſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> By watching continually over the flock, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.9. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the ſecond?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> By being diligent to know the ſtate of his flock, <hi>Prov.</hi> 27.23.<note n="d" place="bottom">This Rule of <hi>Solemon</hi> may fitly applyed to this matter, ſince every Miniſter is a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>Why must he be carefull to know the ſtate of his flock?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> That he may pitty the ignorant, admoniſh the unruly, comfort the fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble minded, bring again that was driven away, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.2. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.16.</p>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:134628:74"/>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the third?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> By giving attendance to reading, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the fourth?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> By not being entangled with the affairs of this life, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the fifth?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> By being inſtant in preaching the Word, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2. and adminiſtring the Sacraments, as occaſion ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the ſixth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> By Catechiſing, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>How elſe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> By being an example to them that believe, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.12.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the puniſhment of a neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent Miniſter?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> God will require the peoples blood at his hands.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>How many things are chiefly ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for him that is to be a Miniſter?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> Two: Firſt, that he hold faſt the Faithful Word, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.9.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, That he be able to exhort
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:134628:74"/> with wholeſome Doctrine, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince them which gain-ſay it, 1 <hi>Tit.</hi> 10.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>§. <hi>5.</hi> The Peoples duty.</head>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the peoples duty in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of ſuch a Miniſter?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> The peoples duty hath five branches.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the firſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> To obey and ſubmit themſelves, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.18.<note n="e" place="bottom">To the ſoundneſs of Doctrine and power of Exhortation.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the ſecond?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> To have him in ſingular love, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd to reverence him, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.13.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the third?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> To make him partakes of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>heir goods, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the fourth?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> To pray for him that utterance may be given him, that he may ſpeak the word as it ought to be ſpoken, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.19. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.4.</p>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:134628:75"/>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the filth?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> To receice no accuſation ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly againſt him, <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.19.<note n="f" place="bottom">It was a direction given, eſpecially to Church-Rulers, but may be applyed to private men.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>Why muſt the people thus carry themſelves to their Miniſter?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> For three cauſes:</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the first?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> Becauſe he worketh the Lords work, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.10.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the ſecond?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> Becauſe he watches over their ſouls, and muſt give an account there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the third?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> Becauſe otherwiſe he ſhall do his duty with grief, which is unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for the people, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17.<note n="i" place="bottom">The Lord ſeeing the grief of his ſoul, will pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh thoſe that cauſed it.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:134628:75"/>
                  <head>§. <hi>6.</hi> Houſhold Duties.</head>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the duty of the Maſter of a Family for matters of Religion?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> To command his Children and and his houſhold to keep the way of the Lord, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19.<note n="k" place="bottom">For this end he muſt have Religious Duties in his Family, as Prayer, Reading, Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, Holy Conference; he muſt alſo bring them to the Miniſtry of the Word in the Publick Congregation.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is his duty for outward things?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> To make proviſion for thoſe of his own Houſhold, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the Wives duty in theſe things?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> To be a help unto her huſband, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.18.<note n="l" place="bottom">Both in matters of Religion, and in outward things.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the mans duty in regard of his Wife?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> To dwel with her as a man of knowledge, and to love her as his own
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:134628:76"/> body, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.28.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the womans duty to her husband?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> To ſubmit her ſelf to him, as unto the Lord, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.22.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>How is that?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> Willingly and chearfully in all lawful things.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is his duty, whom God hath made a Father?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> To bring up his children in the nurture and admonition of the Lord, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.4.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the mothers duty?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> To nouriſh her Children, and inſtruct them, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.1.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the Maſters duty in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his Servants?</hi>
                     <note n="(m)" place="bottom">By Servants are meant, thoſe that are em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed by us in our buſineſs, whether they dwell with us, or otherwiſe.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> To do unto them that which is
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:134628:76"/> juſt and equall, <hi>Col.</hi> 4.1.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is childrens duty to their Parents?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> To obey them in the Lord, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.1.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the reaſon to encourage them to it?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> Fourfold.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the firſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> Becauſe it is right and equall.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the ſecond?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> It is well pleaſing to God, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.20.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the third?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> It is the firſt Commandment with promiſe.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the fourth?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> That it may be well with them, and they may live long in the Land.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is Childrens duty to each other?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> To ſee that they fall not out, <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.24.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the ſervants duty?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> In ſingleneſs of heart, and all
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:134628:77"/> good faithfulneſs to pleaſe their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, yea, though they be froward, <hi>Epheſians</hi> 6.5. <hi>Titus</hi> 2.10. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>§. <hi>7.</hi> The Duty of ſingle Perſons.</head>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is required of Perſons un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>married?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> If they cannot abſtain they muſt marry, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.9.<note n="n" place="bottom">It is a general Commandment appertaining to all ſorts of men.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>How muſt they marry?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> Onely in the Lord, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.39.<note n="o" place="bottom">With Conſent of Parents, and with Care had of Religion.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:134628:77"/>
                  <head>§. <hi>8.</hi> The Duty of Neighbours each to other.</head>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is required of Neighbours that live and converſe together?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> To conſider one another, and provoke to love, and good works, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.24.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>How muſt we be affected in reſpect of thoſe things that happen to our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> We muſt rejoyce with them that rejoyce, and weep with them that weep <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.15. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.7, 8, 9. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28, 29.<note n="o" place="bottom">All things befalling our Neighbour may be referred, either to proſperity or adverſity; therefore this Precept teacheth us how to behave our ſelves towards them in both theſe Eſtates.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>Muſt we rejoyce with all men up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all occaſions?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> No, For folly is joy to him that is deſtitute of underſtanding,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:134628:78"/> and it is a ſport to fools to do miſchief, <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.21. <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.23.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>Muſt we ſhew our ſelves grieved with all men when they are grieved?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> No. In caſe they grieve becauſe they cannot ſin, as <hi>Amnon</hi> did, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.2. or becauſe there are any that ſeek the good of Gods Church, <hi>Neh.</hi> 2.10.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What muſt we do in this caſe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> Be grieved for them, but not with them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.158.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the benefit of a good Neighbour?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> He is better then a Brother afar off, <hi>Prov.</hi> 27.10.<note n="(p)" place="bottom">That is afar off in place or kind affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the beſt means to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve good Neighbours?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> He that hath friends muſt ſhew himſelf friendly, <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.24.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>How is that?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> By bearing one anothers bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:134628:78"/> 
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.2.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>How elſe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> By relieving their miſeries ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our abilities, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.3.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>But how if there be jarring ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> Let not the Sun go down upon your wrath, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.26.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>But what if we be daily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> Be not overcome with evil, but overcome evil with good, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.21.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>But what if my neighbour be my enemy?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> Love your enemies, and pray for them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.44.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>When a man hath many enemies, what is the best way to peace?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> If a mans wayes pleaſe God, he will make his enemies to be at peace with him, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.7.<note n="(q)" place="bottom">Unleſſe God in his Wiſdome ſees it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> for us to be exerciſed with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> wicked men.</note>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:134628:79"/>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>How if a man live in a place ſo wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked it is not ſafe to have familiarity with almoſt any of them?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> He muſt ſtrive to ſhine as a light in a noughty and crooked Generation, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.15.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>§. <hi>9.</hi> A direction concerning Contracts.</head>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>How muſt we carry our ſelves in our dealing towards men?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> We muſt neither Oppreſs<note n="(r)" place="bottom">By hard and extream dealings, as Racking, Uſury, taking Advantage;</note> nor Defraud<note n="(ſ)" place="bottom">By cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and ſubtle courſes, as falſe Weights, Meaſures, &amp;c.</note> any man in any thing, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.6.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the Rule by which all our Contracts muſt be guided?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> Whatſoever we would that men ſhould to us, we muſt do even ſo to them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.12.</p>
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:134628:79"/>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is a good help to this?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> To have our Converſation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Covetouſneſs, and be content with ſuch things as we have, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>Why is this ſuch a help?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> Becauſe the love of money is the root of all evil, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.10.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>§. <hi>10.</hi> The Rich Mans Duty.</head>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the Rich Mans Duty?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> To honour God with his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.9.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>How is that done principally?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> If he be rich in good works, and and ready to diſtribute, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.18.<note n="(t)" place="bottom">By giving or lending freely, <hi>Deut.</hi> 15.8. and ſometime by forgiving debts, <hi>Neh.</hi> 5.9.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What things muſt a rich man take heed of?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> Of high-mindedneſs, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in his wealth, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.17.<note n="(u)" place="bottom">A conceit that he is in Gods favour, and ſuch as he ought to be, becauſe he is Rich.</note>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:134628:80"/>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What muſt be the rich mans joy?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> That he is made low, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.10.<note n="(a)" place="bottom">That is, hath a low mind in a high conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, God having given him Grace to ſee the vanity and uncertainty of riches, and that they commend us not to God.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="section">
                  <head>§. <hi>11.</hi> The poor Mans duty.</head>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the poor mans duty?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> To learn to know how to be in want, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.12.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the poor mans com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> That Chriſt for our ſakes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came poor, that we through his pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty might be made rich, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.9.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the beſt means by which a man may be aſſured while he liveth, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to fall into extremity?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> To ſeek firſt the Kingdome of God, and the righteouſneſs thereof,<note n="(b)" place="bottom">That newneſs of life that becometh the heirs of Gods Kingdom.</note>
                     <pb n="139" facs="tcp:134628:80"/> and then all other things ſhall be added to him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.33.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What muſt be the poor mans joy?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> That he is exalted (to be the Child of God by Grace) <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.9.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="section">
                  <head>§. <hi>12.</hi> The Duty of Aged perſons.</head>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>When is age a Crown of Glory?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> When it is found in the way of Righteouſneſs, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.31.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is the duty of the aged man?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> To be ſober, grave, temperate, ſound in faith, in charity, in patience, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.2.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is required of elder Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> To be of ſuch behaviour as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh holineſs, and to inſtruct the
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:134628:81"/> Younger Women, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.3, 4.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="section">
                  <head>§. <hi>13.</hi> The young perſons duty.</head>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>What be the duties of young folks?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Three eſpecially.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the firſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> To remember their Creator in the dayes of their youth, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.1.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the ſecond?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> To be ſober minded, and to flee the luſts of youth, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.22. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.6.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the third?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> To honour the perſon of the Aged, <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.32.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>What is required of young Women?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> To be diſcreet, chaſt, keepers at home, good, obedient to their own Husbands, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.5.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>Why muſt they thus carry themſelves?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> That they give no occaſion to the adverſary to ſpeak reproachfully, leaſt the Name of God be blaſphemed, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.14. 2 <hi>Tit.</hi> 5.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>Wherewithall ſhall young perſons re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs their way?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> By taking heed thereto according to Gods word, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.9.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="section">
                  <pb n="141" facs="tcp:134628:81"/>
                  <head>§. <hi>14.</hi> The Summe of All.</head>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the brief ſumme of the whole duty of Man?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> To fear God, and k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>p <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.13.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the reward <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> He that doth th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be moved, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.5.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>
               <hi>Glory be to God alone.</hi> AMEN.</trailer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BEfore thou readeſt, mend with thy pen theſe more conſiderable faults in Printing; for points and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maes either mend them thy ſelf or pardon them:</p>
            <p>In <hi>Epiſt. Dedic.</hi> Leaf 1. for ſakes r. ſake. In <hi>Epiſt. to the Reader.</hi> p. 5. l 2. for in r. on. p. 5. l. 19. for mind r. need. p. 17. l. 22. r. adherence. p. 34. l. 9. r. and that not. p. 38. l. 22. for a holy r. the holy. p. 45. l. 20. r. fitted. p. 48. l. 6. r. Banquerouts. p. 61 l. 23. for let r. tell. p. 65. l. 13. r. your ſide. p. 72. l. 10 add (7.) p. 74. l. <hi>penul.</hi> for pulled out r. cannot bite. p. 76 l. 13. for <hi>Eſau</hi> r. <hi>Iſaac.</hi> p. 80. l. 12. r. Corroſive. p. 82 l. 4. add (7) p. 107 l. 1. r. ſix days. p. 64. l. 19. for promiſed r. pronounced.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:134628:82"/>
            <head>Books to be Sold by <hi>Thomas Parkhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Golden Bible</hi> on <hi>London-Bridge.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AN Expoſition of Temptation, on <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. to the end of the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi>: by <hi>Tho. Taylor,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>A learned Commentary or Expoſition on the firſt Chapter of the ſecond Epiſtle to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> by <hi>Richard Sibbs,</hi> D. D. <hi>Fol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A practical Expoſition on the third Chapter of the firſt Epiſtle of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> with the <hi>Godly Mans Choice,</hi> on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4. <hi>verſ.</hi> 6, 7, 8. By <hi>Anthony Burgeſs, Fol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The view of the Holy Scriptures. By <hi>Hugh Broughton. Fol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtianographia,</hi> or a Deſcription of the multitude and ſundry ſorts of Chriſtians in the world, not ſubject to the <hi>Pope.</hi> By <hi>E. Pagit. Fol.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <head>Theſe ſix Treatiſes next following, are written by <hi>Mr. George Swinnock.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>1. The <hi>Chriſtian Mans Calling;</hi> or a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of making Religion ones buſineſs; The firſt Part.</item>
               <item>2. Likewiſe a Second Part.</item>
               <item>3. The third and laſt part of the <hi>Chriſtian Mans Calling.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>The door of Salvation opened</hi> by the <hi>Key of Regeneration.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:134628:82"/>
               <item>5. <hi>Heaven and Hell Epitomized;</hi> and the <hi>True Chriſtian Characterized.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6. The <hi>Fading of the Fleſh,</hi> and the <hi>flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Faith.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>An Expoſition on the five firſt Chapters of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> with uſeful obſervations thereupon; By <hi>Will. Greenhil.</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">to</hi>.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Goſpel Covenant,</hi> or the Covenant of Grace opened: Preached in <hi>New-England,</hi> by <hi>Peter Buckley.</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">to</hi>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gods Holy Mind</hi> touching matters <hi>Moral,</hi> which himſelf uttered in ten words, or ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments; Alſo an Expoſition on the Lords Prayer, by <hi>Edw. Elton,</hi> B. D. 4<hi rend="sup">to</hi>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fiery Jeſuite,</hi> or an Hiſtorical Collection of the Riſe, Increaſe, Doctrines and deeds of the <hi>Jeſuites.</hi> Expoſed for the ſake of <hi>London.</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">to</hi>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Horologiographia Optica; Dialing</hi> univerſall and particular, ſpeculative and practical; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Deſcription of the Court of Arts; A <hi>new method</hi> by <hi>Sylvanus Morgan</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">to</hi>.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Practical Diſcourſe of Prayer,</hi> wherein is handled the Nature and Duty of Prayer; by <hi>Tho. Cobbet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of <hi>Quenching the Spirit,</hi> the evil of it in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect both of its cauſes and effects, diſcovered. By <hi>Theophilus Polwheile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wells of Salvation opened;</hi> or words where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may be ſaved; with advice to young men: by <hi>Tho. Vincent.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:134628:83" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Re-building of <hi>London</hi> encouraged and improved in ſeveral Meditations: by <hi>S. Rolles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The greateſt Loſs, upon <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.26. by <hi>James Liveſey.</hi> ſmall 80.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> unvailed: by <hi>William Guild.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A defence againſt the fear of death:</hi> by Z. <hi>Croft.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gods Soveraignty</hi> diſplayed: by <hi>Will. Geering.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Godly Mans Ark</hi> or City of refuge in the day of his diſtreſs, in five Sermons; with M<hi rend="sup">ris.</hi> 
               <hi>Moores</hi> Evidences for Heaven: by <hi>Ed. Calamy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Almoſt Chriſtian Diſcovered;</hi> or the <hi>Falſe Profeſſor tryed and caſt:</hi> by Mr. <hi>Mead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Spiritual Wiſdom</hi> improved againſt tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: by Mr. <hi>Mead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Divine Cordial.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A word of comfort for the Church of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Plea for Alms,</hi> in a Sermon at the <hi>Spittle:</hi> by <hi>Tho. Watſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>True bounds of Chriſtian freedom:</hi> by <hi>Sam. Bolton</hi> D D. out of <hi>Joh.</hi> 8. <hi>v.</hi> 36.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Lords Day enlivened,</hi> or a Treatiſe of the Sabbath: by <hi>Philip Goodwin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ovid's Metamorphoſis</hi> Tranſlated Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically: by <hi>J. Brinſley.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cloſet Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Chriſtians Duty:</hi> by <hi>Oliver Heywood</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>Hearts Treaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Little Book</hi> for Little Children, by <hi>Thoma. White.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Memento to Young and Old:</hi> by <hi>John May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> late of <hi>Mayfield, Suſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:134628:83"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
